<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The axe at the root of professors miscarriages in a plain detection of, and a wholesome caveat against the miscarriages opposite to faith in God / by Thomas Mall ...</title>
            <author>Mall, Thomas, b. 1629 or 30.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12069</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12426146</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12426146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61858</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51697)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61858)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 945:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The axe at the root of professors miscarriages in a plain detection of, and a wholesome caveat against the miscarriages opposite to faith in God / by Thomas Mall ...</title>
                  <author>Mall, Thomas, b. 1629 or 30.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61858:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Axe at the Root OF PROFESSORS MISCARRIAGES. IN A <hi>Plain Detection</hi> of, and a <hi>Wholſome Caveat</hi> againſt the <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> oppoſite to <hi>Faith in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Mall,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 3.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Now alſo is the Axe laid unto the Root of the Trees; therefore, every Tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewn down, and cast into the fire.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 5.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 7.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If you will not believe, ſurely you ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> upon <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> 1668.</p>
            <p>Sold for 6 <hi>d.</hi> by the Author's Appointm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:61858:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the two firſt ſheets of this Treatiſe, the <hi>Author</hi> hath not found any faults, but in the Marginal Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and he trusts thou wilt find none in the reſt, but what thine ingenuity will correct or pardon. In thoſe ſheets thou maist; <hi>p. 3. for</hi> ſinatis <hi>r.</hi> ſinaris. And <hi>f.</hi> Inarus <hi>r.</hi> Gnarus. <hi>p. 6. for</hi> ſwidas <hi>r.</hi> ſuidas. And <hi>for</hi> juſtus <hi>r.</hi> guſtus. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61858:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Cordial Mourners</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>Exon, Crediton, Tiverton, Taunton, Barnſtable, Bitheferd, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington, Dartmouth,</hi> and <hi>Forey,</hi> for the dreadful <hi>Tokens</hi> of God's <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> againſt <hi>the Land of their Nativity,</hi> and the ſad <hi>Cauſes</hi> thereof; The Author wiſheth Grace and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Hearts,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Doubt not of your kind <hi>acceptance,</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of this honeſt <hi>Eſſay,</hi> to lay the <hi>Axe</hi> of God's Word at the <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>Provocations of God's Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Are not you ſenſible of the <hi>woful</hi> (though but <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi>) <hi>departures</hi> of <hi>your</hi> God from <hi>your own Souls,</hi> and from <hi>the Land of your Nativity?</hi> Are not you <hi>lamenting after the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 7.2. Zach. 11.10, 14. Hoſ. 13.1.</note> Are not you afraid that God is breaking <hi>England's</hi> ſtaff of <hi>Bands,</hi> by breaking its ſtaff of <hi>Beauty?</hi> that even <hi>death</hi> will follow <hi>offending in Baal?</hi> Yea, do not your hearts tremble at the very thoughts of what will farther enſue God's taking away the <hi>Chariots and Horſemen of</hi> your <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 2.12.</note> And would not you take the direct courſe to <hi>re-injoy</hi> the <hi>ſmiles</hi> of your <hi>deareſt Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> and to <hi>prevent England's cutting down?</hi> Yea,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.19.</note> are not you convinced that the <hi>Provocations of God's Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> go <hi>neareſt</hi> to his <hi>hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t?</hi> and that there is no hope even of their <hi>Salvation,</hi> ſo long as <hi>vain thoughts</hi> of eſcaping utter ruine,
<note place="margin">Jer. 4.14.</note> without true repentance <hi>do lodg within them?</hi> And are not you therefore reſolved,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.10.</note> that ſeeing <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>laid</hi> the <hi>Axe</hi> to the <hi>root</hi> of the <hi>Trees,</hi> you will now in good earneſt <hi>lay</hi> the <hi>Axe</hi> to the <hi>root</hi> of <hi>your own Sins?</hi> that you will make it your main buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to promote in your <hi>own Souls,</hi> yea and in <hi>others</hi> too, not only more <hi>humiliation</hi> for, but more <hi>reformation</hi> of what hath been amiſs, as knowing, that <hi>humiliation</hi> without <hi>reformation,</hi> is like the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Letter,</hi> which <hi>kills,</hi> and not <hi>quickens;</hi> it <hi>accents</hi> ſin, and not leſſeneth it; it <hi>continues</hi> judgment, and not <hi>removes</hi> it? For your help therefore herein, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to <hi>detect</hi> and <hi>caution</hi> you againſt <hi>the miſcarriages oppoſite to Faith in God;</hi> which, I dare ſay,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.17. 2 Chr. 18.30.</note> are the <hi>Root</hi> of all your other Miſcarriages: By <hi>the ſword of the Spirit,</hi> and that as welded by the skilful hands of ſeveral of <hi>England's Worthies,</hi> to whom you are refer'd in the Margin; I have fought neither with <hi>ſmall</hi> nor
<pb facs="tcp:61858:3"/>
               <hi>great,</hi> but with your <hi>King-ſins:</hi> It is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>In the day of thy wrath thou ſhalt ſmite through Kings.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.5.</note> And is not this the day of <hi>Chriſts,</hi> yea, of your wrath againſt your <hi>ſins?</hi> Is not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yea, are not <hi>you angry</hi> with them, and <hi>troubled</hi> for them? O then! ſhew that you have the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt</hi> in you; <hi>ſmite through Kings,</hi> I mean only your <hi>Kingly-ſins;</hi> and then I am ſure none will be able to ſtand before you: <hi>Scuh</hi> you will find your ſins oppoſite to <hi>Faith</hi> to be; <hi>each</hi> of them hath <hi>many followers,</hi> and therefore may be called <hi>Gad, Behold a Troop comes.</hi> I have indeed purpoſely waved ſpeaking of the <hi>Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages</hi> oppoſite to <hi>Faith,</hi> with reference to its <hi>immediate</hi> object, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> not only becauſe thoſe are more taken notice of by convinced Souls in theſe days, than theſe with reference to its <hi>ultimate</hi> object, the <hi>Deity through Chriſt:</hi> But becauſe thoſe are moſt excellently handled by the Reverend Author of the late choice <hi>Goſpel-Glaſs, Ch.</hi> 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, to which I ſhall once more refer you, and ſhall detain you no longer from making uſe of this <hi>Axe.</hi> But whilſt I am whiſpering a word or two in the ears of ſuch, as from the Miſcarriages of <hi>ſome</hi> (and not all) Profeſſors, in which they are not <hi>countenanced,</hi> but for which they are <hi>condemned</hi> by <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> are ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſouable as to <hi>fall foul</hi> upon <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">O that ſuch would ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly read ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Mr. <hi>A. Furgeſs</hi>'s 71 <hi>Serm.</hi> in his moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary on <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. I ſhall only tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe for them one paſſage, <hi>fol.</hi> 377. <hi>Would it not have been</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>horrible impiety, to have broken out against all the Apostles, and Christ himſelf; ſaying, Look what they are; It's as the Phariſees ſaid, a company of Impostors and Deceivers, they are all for their own ends, they are all covetous, and though they pretend Religon, yet they are Hypocrites; and though they condemn the groſs ſins of the World, yet in ſecret they can be a bad as any? would not ſuch a tongue ſhew that it was ſet on fire of Hell, that ſhould belch out ſuch things?</hi>
               </note>. It is tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hereby <hi>offences</hi> do come, and <hi>wo be to him by whom offences co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Whoſoever ſhall offend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.7. Mat. 18.7. 1 Pet. 2.7. Joh. 16.1.</note> i. e. lay a ſtumbling-block before <hi>one of Chriſts little ones, it had been better a milſtone were hung about his neck, and he thrown into the Sea.</hi> Wo be to ſuch Profeſſors, that by their being <hi>ſpots, open the mouth of Blaſphemy.</hi> But wo be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo unto all thoſe that take offence againſt <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> thereby. <hi>Wo unto the World becauſe of offences.</hi> Such will be found at laſt to be <hi>Blaſphemers againſt God,</hi> and runners in the broad way to <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Damnation.</hi> Chriſt is a <hi>ſtone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> and a <hi>rock of offence,</hi> only to thoſe that periſh; <hi>to them that believe, he is precious.</hi> This is hinted <hi>that none may be offended,</hi> By your <hi>Faith's</hi> helper,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. M.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 23. 1667.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61858:3"/>
            <head>Of Vain Curioſity.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. I. <hi>The Miſcarriages oppoſite to the ſaving Knowledge of God: the apprehending Act of Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>VAin Curioſity.</hi> Beware not only of <hi>prying</hi> into the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of your <hi>Neighbour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt vain Curioſity.</note> which no way concern you; but of <hi>enquiring</hi> into <hi>Gods</hi> Secrets. God hath made known, enough for our Salvation; but ſome things he hath concealed from us, and they do not belong unto us. <hi>The ſecret things belong unto the Lord our God;
<note place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> but thoſe things which are revealed, belong unto us, and to our children for ever.</hi> Have not you been gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of not con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enting your ſelves with Gods Revelations? Have not you deſired and endeavoured to be wiſe <hi>above what is written?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.6.</note> O the many <hi>curious</hi> and <hi>unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> queſtions, that have been framed about the <hi>Decrees</hi> of God, and the Works of <hi>Providence!</hi> We have not cryed with the Apoſtle, <hi>How unſearchable are his judgements,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33. Gen. 3.5, 6.</note> and his wayes past finding out!</hi> Have not ſome of you been for <hi>new lights?</hi> The <hi>Serpent</hi> beguiled <hi>Eve</hi> hereby: the <hi>firſt</hi> ſin came in by an attempt to get <hi>forbidden knowledge.</hi> And what ſaith the Apoſtle? <hi>I fear, leſt by any means, as the Serpent beguiled</hi> Eve,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.3.</note> 
                  <hi>through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity, that is in Chriſt.</hi> 
                  <q>Have not ſome had the ſame wild fancy,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gilespy</hi>'s Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellan. Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, p. 131.</note> that the <hi>Weigelians</hi> had, That there is a time to come (which they call, <hi>Seculum Spiritus Sancii</hi>) in which God ſhall by his Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal much more knowledge and light, than was revealed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the Scriptures?</q> Are not moſt of us ſtill too inquiſitive, <hi>When Christ will come in his glory, when</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <hi>ſhall fall, when the Witneſſes propheſying in ſackcloth and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hes ſhall be at an end?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Civil</hi> on Job. 28.21.</note> Chriſts own Diſciples were not content with what Chriſt cold them ſhould be, but enquire, <hi>When it ſhould be?</hi> Chriſt doth indeed give them many ſigns of the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of the end of the World; but tells them,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.2, 3.36. Mar. 13.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Of that day and hour knows no man, no not the Angells of Heaven, no nor the Son of Man</hi> (as Man) <hi>but my Father only.</hi> This Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity was alſo reproved by Chriſt, immediately before his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb facs="tcp:61858:4"/>with,
<note place="margin">Acts 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>It is not for you to know the times or ſeaſons which the Father hath put into his own power:</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> That ſuch knowledge was needleſs for them: <hi>But of the times and ſeaſons,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.1.</note> Brethren, you have no need, that I write unto you.</hi> Even good men have ſometimes a ſtronger deſire to <hi>know</hi> the <hi>times,</hi> than to <hi>redeem</hi> the <hi>time.</hi> Hath not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many lain in canvaſing <hi>fooliſh and unlearned queſtions,</hi> which the Apoſtle bids <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>avoid,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.23.</note> becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>end to ſtrife?</hi> O! take heed of this ſin for the future. It is a great Vanity.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cavil</hi> on Job 11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Man is vain</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>when he would be wiſe beyond his line, or in things above him, not in things about him, or ſit for him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thoſe that pry into the ſecrets of <hi>Princes,</hi> may fear what <hi>Actaem</hi> met with; and thoſe that pry into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of <hi>divine myſteries,</hi> what <hi>Pentheus</hi> met with. <hi>Bacon: Sapientia v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum, Sect</hi> 10. Rom. 12.3. Pſa. 25.14. <hi>Cavil</hi> on Job, 28.21. Col. 3.18.</note> It is a ſin that we are naturally prone too. <hi>Man naturally deſires</hi> (as the ſame Author well obſerves) <hi>forbidden wiſdome,</hi> and his deſire is ſeven times ſtronger after it, as it is <hi>forbidden,</hi> than as it is <hi>wiſdome.</hi> This is a ſin very provoking unto God: To pry into, <hi>dreana imperij,</hi> the myſteries of their government is ſo unto Princes. No wonder that God hath been <hi>a emſwning fire</hi> to us, ſeeing we have been ſo bold and daring <hi>Phaetons.</hi> Vain Curioſity is a preſumptuous tranſgreſſion: take heed of continuing guilty thereof any longer: for the future be wiſe <hi>unto ſobriety.</hi> Though <hi>the ſecret of the Lord be with thoſe that fear him,</hi> yet they, that fear him, will not, dare not, meddle with, nor ſearch into his ſecrets. Take heed of breaking open of God, Cabinet, entring into his Counſels, prying into his Ark once more: beware of ſuffering your imagination to wax wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and run riot, yea mad about crotchets, and meer niceties any more: take heed of <hi>intruding</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantly to this point) <hi>into things which you have not ſeen,</hi> yea, <hi>which cannot be ſeen,</hi> being <hi>vainly puft up by your fleſhly mind.</hi> There is (ſaith the ſame judicious Expoſitor <hi>fleſh</hi> in the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> as well as in the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> of man; and in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> there is <hi>pride,</hi> and it is pride, that makes men ſo buſie and bold; ſo boldly buſie, as (un-ask'd, yea forbidden) to intrude into ſuch things.
<note place="margin">Pſa. 131.1.</note> O! ſay now with <hi>David, Lord, mine Feart is not haughty, nor mine eyes lofty, neither will I exerciſe my ſelf in great matters, or in things too high for me.</hi> Such are things not revealed: they are not only <hi>high things;</hi> but above the lawfulneſs of mans ſearch:
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.16. Rom. 11.33.</note> they are tearmed not <hi>incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> but rather <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, things <hi>not to be enquired into. Who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to open the Book?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 5.3.</note> Who, <hi>but the Lyon of the Tribe of</hi> Judah?
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61858:4"/>The beſt of Gods Saints are ſo unfit to <hi>expound</hi> the <hi>contents</hi> of the Book, wherein the myſteries of Providence lye coucht,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Genus quaſi ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crileg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>emeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis eſt, ut plus ſcire cupias, quam ſmatis.</hi> Salts.</note> and inſolded, that they may not ſo much as <hi>untye</hi> the <hi>claſps.</hi> A bold enquiry here is not more <hi>irreverent,</hi> than full of <hi>danger.</hi> When men walk on <hi>ſleep</hi> places, they are ſubject to <hi>fall:</hi> ſo here, by medling with <hi>high things,</hi> an <hi>errour,</hi> yea <hi>hereſie,</hi> is quickly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ignorance.</hi> I do not ſay, take heed of <hi>Neſcience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> of not knowing thoſe things, which you are not <hi>bound</hi> to know, or have not <hi>means</hi> to know; in the former Section I have cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned you againſt ſuch <hi>ſcience:</hi> But beware of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> of not knowing what you <hi>ought</hi> to know, and what you <hi>have means</hi> to know. Hath not this been your ſin? Hath not <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> come in <hi>flaming fire</hi> againſt this ſin? O that it may be your ſin no more! What! Is it yet nothing to you, that your Souls ſhould remain as <hi>Lanthorns</hi> without <hi>Candles</hi> in them? Is it yet nothing to you, to want <hi>eye-ſight,</hi> to have <hi>blind Souls?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.13. 2 Cor. 4.3, 4. <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dwins</hi> Evangelical Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> q. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, peritas.</hi> Leigh. <hi>crit. ſacr.</hi>
                  </note> to have the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſtill <hi>hid</hi> from you, as ſo many <hi>loſt</hi> Souls, <hi>blinded by the god of this world?</hi> Have you no mind as yet to be freed from <hi>Satans ſlavery? Satan</hi> doth indeed ſometimes <hi>transform himſelf into an Angel of light;</hi> but he alwayes loves to dwell in a <hi>dark houſe,</hi> in an ignorant Soul: Though his Name be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and he <hi>hath</hi> much knowledge himſelf, yet he <hi>hates</hi> and <hi>hinders</hi> knowledge in man: He knows, he hath none more <hi>faſt,</hi> than thoſe that ye in the dark Dungeon of Ignorance, <hi>bound</hi> in the <hi>chains</hi> of <hi>darkneſs.</hi> Is it nothing to you, to continue ſtill <hi>ſtark nargi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> without any goodneſs in your hearts? As the <hi>mind</hi> is, ſo is the <hi>man. Without knowledge, the heart is not good.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 19.2.</note> For any to ſay, Though I am <hi>ignorant,</hi> yet mine <hi>heart</hi> is <hi>good,</hi> is as if one ſhould ſay, Though I am <hi>blind,</hi> yet mine <hi>eyes</hi> are <hi>good.</hi> Thoſe that had the <hi>lepreſſe</hi> in the <hi>head,</hi> were to be judged <hi>unclean.</hi> Is it nothing to you, ſtill to remain <hi>uſeleſs unto others?</hi> Is it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to you, to be even in ſuch times as theſe, without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in God, <hi>ſtrangers from the life of God through ignorance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.18.</note> ſo as none of Gods ofters of himſelf do yet prevail with you? Is it nothing to you, to continue <hi>prepared for ruine?
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 1.14.</note> The people that underſtand not,</hi> ſhall not only <hi>ſtumble,</hi> but <hi>fall, i. e.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ally pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. O ye <hi>ignorant</hi> Profeſſions!
<note place="margin">Rev. 6.17.</note> 
                  <hi>the great day of Gods wrath</hi> is coming, and how will ye <hi>be able to ſtand? O that you would yet know the things, that belong to your peace,
<note place="margin">Luc. 19.42.</note> before they be hid from your eyes!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:61858:5"/>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Againſt Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>your.</note> 
                  <hi>Errour.</hi> Take heed not only of <hi>not apprehending,</hi> but of <hi>miſ apprehending</hi> God, and the things of God. Hath not this been your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>? Have not your apprehenſions concerning God been very erroneous? Have not ſome Profeſſors thought, That there is no God, nor Devil, nor Heaven, nor Hell, but what is within us; and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and grace were equally of God, and agrecable to his will? O! <hi>Be not</hi> alwayes <hi>deceived</hi> concerning the <hi>Providence</hi> of God, his <hi>Worſhip,</hi> his <hi>Miniſiry,</hi> his <hi>Houſe,</hi> his <hi>Diſcipline in his houſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Brook</hi>'s Satans wiles. Rom. 1.28.</note> &amp;c.</hi> Is it nothing to you, to be under the <hi>Gentiles</hi> heavy and dreadful <hi>Plague,</hi> to be given up to <hi>a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind,</hi> a mind <hi>void of judgement,</hi> a mind <hi>diſallowed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,</hi> and <hi>abhorred of God;</hi> a mind <hi>that all have cauſe to be aſhamed of?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 cor. 3 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> Is it nothing to you, to <hi>ſuffer loſs</hi> in Gods <hi>reſiuing fire?</hi> Is it nothing to you, ſtill to entertain that <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oriſh woman,</hi> that hath <hi>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> down</hi> many, <hi>wounded</hi> many, yea <hi>ſlain</hi> many, many <hi>ſtrong</hi> men, many <hi>great</hi> men, many <hi>learned</hi> men, yea many <hi>Profeſſing</hi> men?
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.10, 11, 12.</note> Is it nothing to you, to be ſtill in danger of Gods ſending upon you <hi>ſtrong deluſions,</hi> or (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Greek</hi> hath it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) the efficacy of errour, <hi>that you ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a lye,</hi> the lye of lyes, <hi>viz., Popery, that you may be damned?</hi> Ah Souls! Can you ſeriouſly conſider theſe hints, and thoſe you have in the <hi>Goſpel-glaſs, chap.</hi> 9. and not dread, and ſtand upon your guard, againſt every Errour in Religion? True <hi>hatred</hi> is to the <hi>whole kind.</hi> It is ſad to <hi>frown</hi> on <hi>one</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and to <hi>ſmile</hi> on <hi>another. Gideon</hi> had <hi>ſeventy</hi> ſons, and but one <hi>baſtard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg: 8.13.</note> and yet <hi>the baſtard deſtroyed all the rest.</hi> One turn may bring a man quite out of his way. <hi>Ah Lord!</hi> (ſaid one) <hi>this mercy I humbly beg, that thou would rather take me, and do any thing with me, than to give me up to thoſe ſad Errours, to which thouſands have married their Souls, and are in a way of periſhing eternally.
<note place="margin">Jam 1.16.</note> O! Do not erre, my beloved Brethren.</hi> Take heed therefore of <hi>pride,</hi> of that <hi>proud Curioſity</hi> I have already cautioned you againſt. <hi>The meek,</hi> or humble (as the word ſignifieth) <hi>will he guide in judgement, the meek will he teach his way.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 25.9.</note> The ſame Author tells of a man, who, ſeeing in a Viſion many <hi>ſnares</hi> of the Devil, ſpread upon the earth, ſate down muſing, and ſaid within himſelf, <hi>Who ſhall paſs through theſe?</hi> Whereunto he heard a voice anſwering, <hi>Humility ſhall paſs through them.</hi> To <hi>perſist wilfully</hi> in <hi>Errour</hi> is <hi>Diabolical.</hi> It were <hi>beſt,</hi> we never erred; <hi>next to that,</hi> that we amend our Errours.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61858:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Take heed of being <hi>cententious</hi> againſt the truth,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and <hi>diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> to the truth, when made known unto you: yea take heed of a voluntary <hi>ſluggiſhneſs,</hi> and an aſſected <hi>lazineſs,</hi> as to <hi>ſearching</hi> out of <hi>Truth,</hi> which cannot but <hi>expoſe</hi> a man to <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour;</hi> for Truth doth comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dy keep ſo much State,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> as not to reveal her ſelf to any, but thoſe who ſtudiouſly ſeek her. Take heed alſo of <hi>Covetouſneſs.</hi> In a word, be careful to ſubdue all your inordinate affections; for they are of great force to ſway the Judgement.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nteachableneſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teachableneſs.</note> Take heed of unwillingneſs to get <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>right</hi> apprehenſions of God. Hath not this been your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Have not you been not only <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>erroneous,</hi> but <hi>unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to be inſtructed? Have not you been not only <hi>deſtitute of,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d eſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but <hi>oppoſite to,</hi> the ſaving knowledge of God? Light hath been offered; but have not you ſhut your eyes againſt it? And if ſome light hath broke in upon you,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.19.</note> you have <hi>not liked to retain God in your knowledge.</hi> Have you not wilfully <hi>rejected knowledge?</hi> and hath not <hi>God</hi> therefore <hi>rejected you?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6. See <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> on the place:</note> Have not you <hi>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> off</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of God, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>contempt,</hi> and <hi>deſpite,</hi> as the word ſignifyeth? Have not you <hi>caſt off</hi> the <hi>means</hi> of knowledge? And hath not <hi>God</hi> therefore <hi>took away</hi> the <hi>means</hi> of knowledge? Have not you thought, that you muſt buſie your heads about ſome other matters; and that you may do well enough with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this knowledge, if you do but know how to trade, and to mannage your worldly buſineſſes? Have not you <hi>rejected</hi> the knowledge of that Truth eſpecially, that ſhould have brought you to the true worſhip of God, as thoſe Prieſts did the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that they muſt worſhip God at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for fear of loſing their eſtates? Hath not God therefore, in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner, rejected you? So much is noted (thinks <hi>Tremellius</hi>) by the redundancy of a letter in the word for Gods rejecting, not found elſewhere in all the Scripture. <hi>Have not you even ſtudied to be ignorant of God?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> on H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. 4 1.</note> Have not you therefore been for <hi>unteaching Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>humane inventions,</hi> in the worſhip of God, which kept out of the Land of <hi>Iſrael</hi> the knowledge of God? No wonder that <hi>God hath a controverſie with the Land,</hi> no wonder that God is contending with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Profeſſors in a way of judgement; no wonder if there be <hi>no peace in</hi> England, <hi>to him that goeth out, and cometh in,
<note place="margin">2 chron. 15, 3.5.</note> but great vexations upon all the Inhabitants, God vexing us with all adoer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61858:6"/>So it was with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the like caſe, <hi>Iſrael was without the true God, i. e.</hi> the true worſhip of God, <hi>and without a teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and in thoſe times there was no peace, &amp;c.</hi> No wonder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at <hi>God hath made us to ſee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſeeing <hi>we would not ſee:</hi> No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>God is departed from us,</hi> ſeeing we have ſaid, at leaſt in our hearts,
<note place="margin">Job <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſee <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> on Job 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes.</hi> Your <hi>Ignorance</hi> hath <hi>much</hi> incented God againſt you; but your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nteachableneſs</hi> much <hi>more.</hi> O! <hi>dequaint now thy ſelf with him.</hi> I beſeech you <hi>now, now</hi> that the hand of God is out againſt your ſelves, in ſome kind or other; <hi>now</hi> that the hand of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. much heavier upon others; <hi>now dequaint your ſelves with him; now or never; now,</hi> or elſe he will not <hi>be at peace</hi> with you, and <hi>good will</hi> not <hi>come unto you.</hi> Let it not alwayes be ſaid. <hi>They know not,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſa.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.3.</note> neither will they underſtand, they walk on in darkneſs.</hi> O! unto <hi>reading</hi> and <hi>hearing,</hi> add <hi>praying,</hi> that you may not only be <hi>Book-taught,</hi> but <hi>God-taught.</hi> You need not <hi>aſcend up into Heaven. to bring Chriſt down from above, nor to deſcend into the deep,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.6.</note> to bring, up Chriſt from the dead,</hi> that you may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him;
<note place="margin">John 17.3.</note> 
                  <hi>the Word is nigh you,</hi> which being read, heard, and prayed over, will give you that <hi>knowledge of God and Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>is life eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Againſt reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Form of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Rom. 2.20. <hi>Map<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>er, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cidas.</hi> Jam. 3: 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing in a Form of Knowledge.</hi> The word ſignifieth the <hi>ſhew,</hi> the <hi>appearance,</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> of Knowledge. Hath not this been your ſin? Have not you affected the <hi>reputation</hi> of knowledg, more than the <hi>reality</hi> of knowledg? Hath not the <hi>Name</hi> been better eſteem'd by you, than the <hi>Thing?</hi> Have not you ſatisfied your ſelves with <hi>a dark and confuſed knowledge?</hi> Hath not your <hi>light</hi> been <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? The wiſdome from above is pure,</hi> and therefore <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>diſtinct.</hi> Have not you ſatisfied your ſelves with <hi>a ſupleſs know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> without the <hi>favour,</hi> that is in ſaving knowledge? <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> in Scripture doth connote <hi>affection;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">It is tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> men, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and that, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth not the heart and affections with it, deſerveth not the name of Knowledge; and therefore thoſe, that did not <hi>like</hi> and <hi>love</hi> God, are ſaid, <hi>not to know God.</hi> Have not you ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied your ſelves <hi>without an experimental knowledge</hi> of God, of the exerciſe of his Power, Wiſdome, Goodneſs, Mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for your eternal welfare, in working effectually upon your hearts, by his Word and Spirit? Have not you ſatisfied your ſelves with an <hi>unactive knowledge?</hi> To have <hi>notions</hi> according to <hi>Knowledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer: 10: 14:</note> and <hi>actions</hi> according to <hi>Ignorance,</hi> is to be <hi>bruitiſh
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61858:6"/>in knowledge.</hi> Have not you ſet up your reſt, in ſuch acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as is ſhort of making men live <hi>peaceably, humbly, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently,</hi> and <hi>believingly,</hi> as ſaying knowledge doth? This Kind of knowledge, i.b.t <hi>a form of knowledge,</hi> without the <hi>truth, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,</hi> and <hi>reality</hi> of knowledge; <hi>as a form of godlineſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim: 3: 5: <hi>Verban ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> connotant affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum &amp; effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi> Job 28: 28: Pſa: 111: 10:</note> is the <hi>appearance</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> godlineſs, <hi>without the payer of godlineſs.</hi> The knowledge of God doth note <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>barren nations</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God, which do not render <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>better</hi> in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lives, or <hi>liker</hi> unto God. <hi>He knee no ſin.</hi> in <hi>Paul,</hi> is in <hi>Peter, He did no ſin. To depart from evil, is underſtanding. They ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that do his Commandements. Joſiah</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtreet in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming his known duty, And <hi>was not this, to know me,
<note place="margin">Jer: 22, 16:</note> ſaith the Lord?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch as do not <hi>dwake to righteouſneſs,</hi> (the <hi>Greek</hi> is <hi>awake righteouſly</hi>) <hi>i. e.</hi> that do not give their minds and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to righteouſneſs, they <hi>have not the knowledge of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor: 15: 31:</note> Have not you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tisfied your ſelver, <hi>without knowing God in and through Chriſt?</hi> Here let it be minded,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>T: G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>win</hi>'s Chriſtier forth, <hi>p:</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that the Object of that Faith, that is required in the firſt Commandement, in all its acts, both <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>reflect, inward</hi> and <hi>outward,</hi> is God in Chriſt, or intereſt in God in and through Chriſt. The Deity, Father, Son, and Spirit, is the <hi>ultimate</hi> Object; but Jeſus Chriſt, God dwelling in fleſh,
<note place="margin">Eph: 2: 18: 1 Pet: 1: 21:</note> is the more <hi>immediate</hi> Object thereof. Chriſt <hi>leads</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s by the hand, and we are ſaid <hi>by Christ to believe on God, that our Faith might be in God.</hi> But have you ever had a <hi>real</hi> and <hi>intuitive</hi> ſight of Jeſus Chriſt in his glory,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sheph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> on the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able of the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gins, p: 74, 75, 202, 203, 204:</note> not only from <hi>report,</hi> nor only from his <hi>works,</hi> nor only from the bare <hi>letter of the Word,</hi> but from the <hi>Spirit?</hi> Have you ever beheld ſuch a glory in Chriſts perſon, as hath cauſed you to eſteem him in all his glory, as your <hi>preſent, greatest</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> good?
<note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4: 6:</note> Hath God ever given you <hi>the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> If not, you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of your <hi>Knowledge</hi> under the notion of <hi>Ignorance;</hi> and be ſure, that for the future you be reſtleſs after a <hi>clear, distinct, ſavory, experimental, active</hi> Knowledge of God <hi>in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Not growing in Knowledge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt not growing in Knowledge <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 3, 4, 5.</note> Is not <hi>ſaving</hi> knowledge a <hi>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> thing? Were not the <hi>riſings</hi> and <hi>increaſings of the waters of the Sanctuary</hi> a <hi>type</hi> thereof? But ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have not the beſt ſet up their reſt in low attainments of ſaving knowledge? Have not ſome conceited themſelves taught by God <hi>immediately,</hi> by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and needed not any of Gods <hi>medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> teachings, by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61858:7"/>the <hi>miniſtry</hi> of man, or by the <hi>Scriptures?</hi> As for ſuch, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever knowledge they pretend to, the truth is, they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without the ſaving knowledge of God. <hi>As he</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>who thinks himſelf ſo good, that he cannot be better, was never ſo good as he ſhould be: So he that thinks he knows ſo much, as he can learn no more,
<note place="margin">1 Cor: 8: 2:</note> from the Scriptures and Mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry, know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nothing as he ought.</hi> As for thoſe, that have the beginnings of <hi>life eternal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 17: 3:</note> in the knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it hath been their great fault, that they have not made conſcience of growing in knowledge daily; both of getting the knowledge of more <hi>duties,</hi> and of more <hi>ſins;</hi> and more of the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of thoſe duties, and of the <hi>evil</hi> of thoſe ſins, which they knew already, as they ought How ſeldome have Sermons been attended for this very end? How ſeldome have Miniſters been conſulted with for this very end? <hi>Doth not your not grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in grace evidence, that you have not grown in knowledge?</hi> The Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle puts both together;
<note place="margin">2 Pet: 3: 18:</note> 
                  <hi>Grow in grace, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> to hint to us, that in proportion to our ſpiritual growth in knowledge, is our growth in grace. <hi>Is not your neglect of growing in knowledge, evident in your decayes in knowledge;</hi> not ſeeing ſo much <hi>evil</hi> in <hi>ſin,</hi> eſpecially ſuch and ſuch <hi>particular</hi> ſins; nor ſo much <hi>good</hi> in <hi>duty,</hi> eſpecially ſuch and ſuch <hi>particular</hi> duties; nor ſo much <hi>beauty</hi> in <hi>truth,</hi> eſpecially ſuch and ſuch <hi>particular</hi> truths; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo much <hi>deformity</hi> in <hi>errour,</hi> eſpecially ſuch and ſuch <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> errours, as formerly. No wonder that God deals with us, as he hath threatned to deal with them, that know him not. No wonder if God ſeem to reſolve, that this generation of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Profeſſors, ſhall not enter into the promiſed <hi>Canaan; They were thoſe that had not known Gods wayes, to whom the Lord ſwore, that they ſhould not enter into his reſt.</hi> To prevent this, let us all be ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'d up, to <hi>conform</hi> more and more <hi>to Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who <hi>grew in wiſdome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as well as <hi>in ſtature.</hi> Let us write after <hi>Paul</hi>'s copy,
<note place="margin">Phil: 3: 12, 13, 14:</note> 
                  <hi>Not as though I had already attained, or were already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but I follow after, if that I may apprehend, that for which alſo I am apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus: Brethren, I count not my ſelf to have apprehended; but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth to thoſe things that are before, I preſs toward the mark, &amp;c.</hi> Would you have God take away all your talents? Take heed then of neglecting to
<pb facs="tcp:61858:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>increaſe them. <hi>Then ſhall yee know, if yee follow on to know the Lord. The path of the juſt is as the ſhining Light,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.3. Prov. 4.18.</note> that ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth more and more, till it be perfect Day.</hi> 
                  <q>He (ſaith one) that hath the <hi>leaſt</hi> ſaving acquaintance with God, hath enough to make him <hi>thankful;</hi> but he that hath the <hi>moſt,</hi> hath not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make him <hi>idle.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Neglecting to make uſe of Knowledge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt not ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king uſe of knowledge.</note> Hath not this been your ſin? Hath not the habit of knowledge layn dead in your Souls? Hath it not been an uſeleſs and an unprofitable thing, both as to your ſelves, and others? O that it may be your ſin no more! Be not ſatisfied with having Lights, or Lamps,
<note place="margin">Luc. 12.35.</note> but <hi>Let your Lights be burning,</hi> or ſhining. Make uſe of your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>for the heating of your affections,</hi> for the ſtirring up <hi>deſires</hi> after God, <hi>love</hi> to God, <hi>delight</hi> in God, <hi>hatred</hi> of ſin, <hi>fear</hi> of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As the Spouſe, <hi>He is altogether lovely:
<note place="margin">Cant. 5.16.</note> This is my Beloved. Let the knowledge of wiſdome be unto your Souls, as Honey, that is good, and the Honey-comb,
<note place="margin">Prov. 24.13, 14</note> which is ſweet unto the taſt.</hi> Make uſe of your knowledge <hi>for the guiding of your thoughts words and actions. Let wiſdome guide</hi> you in every ſtep you take.
<note place="margin">Prov. 6.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Ask of your knowledge continually, what ſaith the Rule? what doth the Word of God require? Make uſe of your knowledge <hi>in bearing witneſs to truth, for which you came into this World.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 18.36.</note> When you come to appear for an oppoſed truth, let not your knowledge be to ſeek. Make uſe of your knowledge <hi>for the preſerving of your Souls from theoretical and practical miſcariages. Seeing yee know, &amp;c. beware leſt yee alſo be led away with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the wicked.</hi> If you will make uſe of your knowledge,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16: Prov. 2.11, 12, 16.</note> you have Gods promiſe for preſervation from <hi>ſnares</hi> in judgment, and <hi>defilements</hi> in practice. The Devil ſhall not <hi>undermine</hi> you by <hi>policy,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>overcome</hi> you by <hi>power.</hi> Make uſe of your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>for the good of others.</hi> One great <hi>end</hi> of knowledge is to <hi>communicate</hi> knowledge. And indeed (as one well obſerves) <hi>to know for our own and others good is the only good knowledge.</hi> To <hi>reject</hi> the <hi>directions</hi> of knowledge, as well as the <hi>means</hi> of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is to <hi>reject knowledge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bur.</hi> on Hof. 4.6</note> And hath not <hi>God</hi> therefore <hi>reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> you? Is not God reckoning with his <hi>wicked,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> ſervants, for letting their Talents lie un-improved? Yea, is not this a greater judgment than any outward judgments you are under? Is it not an evidence of a Souls being under a <hi>ſpirit of ſlumber,</hi> to have no more uſe of its knowledge,
<note place="margin">Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.10.</note> then one
<pb facs="tcp:61858:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>aſleep hath? <hi>Not to uſe</hi> is all one as <hi>not to have</hi> knowledge. <hi>He that hath not, i.e.</hi> that doth not make uſe of what he hath, <hi>ſhall have what he hath, or ſeems to have, taken away from him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. II. <hi>The miſcarriages oppoſite to Believing God? The Aſsenting Act of Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Againſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity. Prov.</hi> 14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>VAin Credulity.</hi> Hath not this been your ſin? Have not you been ſo <hi>ſimple</hi> as to <hi>believe every word,</hi> pretending to come from God? <hi>Have not you been ready to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ken to falſe Teachers?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 4.24. <hi>mat.</hi> 7.15. Jer. 23.16. mar. 8.15.</note> Though God hath ſaid, <hi>Take heed what you hear: Beware of falſe Prophets: Hearken not unto the words of the Prophets, that propheſie unto you, they make you vain, they ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Viſion of their own heart: Take heed, beware of the leaven of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hariſees, and of the leaven of Herod;</hi> yet how <hi>fool hardy</hi> and venturous have you been? O the ſad conſequences of this fool-hardineſs! <hi>Eve</hi> loſt all by hearing <hi>one</hi> Sermon from the mouth of the <hi>Serpent. Julian</hi> the Emperor, ſipt in his <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Libanius,</hi> the Sophiſter. Let others, yea your own harms, make you to beware.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faelix quem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt aliena pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricula, &amp;c. Prov.</hi> 9.18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.</note> O! come not any more neer the do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of their houſe; <hi>Knoweſt thou not that the dead are there, and that their gueſts are in the depth of Hell?</hi> Say not, you muſt <hi>try all things;</hi> Chriſtians ought indeed to <hi>prove all things</hi> in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſenſe; the Doctrines, that Chriſts own Miniſters teach them, they muſt bring to the touch-ſtone of the Word; But he that will adventure to taſt of every box and glaſs in an <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> ſhop, may ſooner meet with <hi>poyſon,</hi> than with <hi>nutriment. Have not you been ready to receive and reject Doctrines, before you have brought them to the touch-ſtone and ballance of the Sanctuary, to be tryed?</hi> Before you receive or reject a piece of gold, you will go to the <hi>touch-ſtone,</hi> to try whether it be good <hi>mettal,</hi> or no, and to the <hi>ballance</hi> to try whether it be <hi>weight,</hi> or no; But have you not dealt otherwiſe with the Doctrines you have heard?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ril</hi> on Job 12: 11:</note> Hath your <hi>ear tryed the words,</hi> that have ſounded therein? The Original word for an ear (as an excellent Expoſitor obſerves) being of the <hi>dual</hi> Number, ſignifieth <hi>a pair of ballances,</hi> to note, that <hi>we ſhould not only hear, but weigh.</hi> But <hi>have not you received Doctrines upon truſt?</hi> Have not ſome given an <hi>abſolute credence</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> to a <hi>Synod,</hi> to a <hi>Councel?</hi> Have not others to this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61858:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the other <hi>ſingular perſon,</hi> if a <hi>learned</hi> Man, or a <hi>pious</hi> Man, if a <hi>Paſtor,</hi> or a <hi>Teacher,</hi> eſpecially, if pretending the <hi>ſpirit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation?</hi> But what faith the Apoſtle? <hi>We beſeech you, brethren,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.2.</note> that yee be not ſoon ſhaken in mind, or be troubled, neither by</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>nor by</hi> word, <hi>nor by</hi> letter, <hi>as from us;</hi> not by <hi>ſpirit,</hi> thoſe that pretend <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phetical revelations;</hi> nor <hi>word,</hi> thoſe that plead <hi>tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> nor <hi>letter,</hi> thoſe that urge <hi>forged records.</hi> It was the <hi>Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> commendation,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.11.</note> that they would not truſt <hi>Paul</hi> upon his word, but <hi>tryed</hi> his <hi>Doctrine</hi> by the <hi>Scriptures. Have not you alſo rejected Doctrines upon truſt?</hi> It is as dangerous (ſaith one) to <hi>refuſe,</hi> as to receive, what we have not <hi>examined.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Shephard</hi>'s wholeſome caveat for a time of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>p.</hi> 3: <hi>Aſh</hi> on 2 Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 30.8. 1 Cor. 7, 23. <hi>mat.</hi> 23.10.</note> No wonder that we, that have been ſo ready to <hi>inſlave</hi> our <hi>conſciences</hi> to Men, be given up to ſo ſoar a bondage. <hi>They ſhall be his ſervants, that they may know my ſervice, and the ſervice of the Kingdomes of the Country; i.e.</hi> That they may know the <hi>difference</hi> between them: the <hi>bondage</hi> of the one, and the <hi>liberty</hi> of the other. O that this may be your ſin no more! why ſhould ye be any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er willing to be the <hi>ſervants of Men,</hi> ſeeing <hi>one is your Master, which is Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Sinful Incredulity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Againſt Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Credere, fidem habere, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere.</hi>
                  </note> The aſſenting act of faith is a full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of any truth upon a divine teſtimony. The <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Latines</hi> expreſs it by ſuch words, as import <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving,</hi> or <hi>giving credit to.</hi> Many think all <hi>Infidels</hi> are without the <hi>pale</hi> among <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens;</hi> But alas! are not too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny found in the <hi>boſomes</hi> of <hi>Churches?</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were Gods people, and yet <hi>deſtroyed</hi> in the Wilderneſs, becauſe <hi>they believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not.</hi> And may not we fear deſtruction for our unbelief?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Capel</hi> of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prations, <hi>page</hi> 153, 154.</note> 
                  <hi>Are not we ſtill guilty of not believing that God is, what God is, and what God ſaith?</hi> One well obſerves, that <hi>all ſin comes from Atheiſme; for who would ſin, did he then verily believe, that there were a God, that ſaw all, and would puniſh all? And ſuch a God, God muſt be, or no God: And all ſin tends to Atheiſme; for ſin wipes out all the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Deity, as much as it can: And when we are in ſin, we muſt be either willing to get out of it by Repemance, or elſe we ſhall be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to turn Atheists. Guilt</hi> always (ſaith another) begets <hi>fear;</hi> and <hi>fear, hatred;</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> ſtrikes at the <hi>being</hi> of the <hi>object hated:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bates</hi> on Heb. 11.6. in <hi>M. E.</hi> at <hi>G. page</hi> 52. <hi>Gedolphins holy Arbor, page</hi> 17</note> as is evident in <hi>Malefactors,</hi> deſiting there were no <hi>Law,</hi> nor <hi>Judge.</hi> Do not we <hi>ſay</hi> in our hearts, <hi>there is no God?</hi> ſo <hi>the fool,</hi> the ſinner doth. It is Atheiſme (ſaith one) when Men do but in their hearts ſay that it is all vanity which is ſpoken of God.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61858:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Are not we ſtill guilty of <hi>not believing what God is?</hi> Do not we <hi>deny,</hi> if not <hi>expreſly,</hi> yet <hi>conſequentially Gods abſolute dominion</hi> to command us: the <hi>goodneſs</hi> as well as <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of the law of God, by which we ought to be ruled: that he is the <hi>rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them that diligently ſeeke him,</hi> and the <hi>avenger</hi> of his <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries;</hi> that <hi>he ſees our thoughts afar off,</hi> and that our greateſt <hi>ſecrets are naked and open to, anatomized, and diffected before,</hi> his eyes: that he is <hi>good,</hi> yea <hi>the chief good?</hi> Are not we ſtill guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>not believing what God ſaith,</hi> which of us is yet fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that our loſſes for Chriſt ſhall be made up with the hundred fold in this life; becauſe he hath ſaid, <hi>Verily, there is no Man that hath left Houſe,
<note place="margin">Luk. 18.29, 30. mat. 19, 29.</note> or Parents, or Brethren, or Wife, or Children, for the Kingdome of Gods ſake, who ſhall not receive many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold in this preſent time: He ſhall</hi> (according to <hi>Matthew</hi>) <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an hundred fold?</hi> Which of us yet believes that God will repay what ever we lay out for his poor ſervants, becauſe he hath ſaid,
<note place="margin">Prov. 19.17.</note> 
                  <hi>He that hath pity on the poor, lendeth to the Lord, and that, which he hath given, will be pay him again?</hi> Which of us yet believes, that if we will be Chriſts witneſſes, none of the World will cordially love us;
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.22.</note> becauſe he hath ſaid, <hi>yee ſhall be hated of all Men for my names ſake?</hi> Which of us yet believes that all <hi>Hells</hi> and the <hi>Worlds</hi> hatred can do a Child of God no hurt, becauſe he hath ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are yee, when Men ſhall revile you,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.11.</note> and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my Names ſake?</hi> We are indeed apt to beguile our ſelves and others, in profeſſing that we receive Gods teſtimony in all that he ſpeaks; but the Apoſtle tells us, there is a <hi>denial of God in works,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</note> as well as in <hi>words:</hi> and certainly denial in works is the ſtrongeſt denial, and manifeſts that our affirming what God ſaith in words is but meer <hi>hypocriſie:</hi> that we do but <hi>flatter God with our mouth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73, 35 compared with <hi>v.</hi> 40, 41.</note> and lie unto him with our tongues.</hi> Are not we ſtill guilty of neglecting to get our hearts more and more eſtabliſhed in believing that God is, what God is, and what God ſaith? Is not this a lamentation, and ſhould it not be for a lamentation? ſhould we not mainly repent of our <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief,</hi> ſeeing it is not only the <hi>provocation,</hi> but the cauſe of all our other provocations?
<note place="margin">Hebr. 3, 8.</note> No wonder that God hath ſhamed the throne of our glory, ſeeing we have rob'd God of his glory by our unbelief? What is Gods declarative glory, but his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the World? Unbelief takes away Gods reputation,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61858:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>it makes him of no credit in the World, it <hi>makes him a lyar.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 5: 10. Rom. 3.3.</note> By <hi>unbelief</hi> we attempt to make <hi>the faith of God, i. e.</hi> his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>of none effect.</hi> O! repent, repent that God, who is <hi>no debtor</hi> to you, who was <hi>never worſe</hi> then his word, hath ſo little credit with you, who profeſs to be his <hi>ſervants,</hi> his <hi>children,</hi> his <hi>ſpouſes.</hi> No wonder that we are kept in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> yea in a manner <hi>brought back</hi> into <hi>Egypt:</hi> We may thank our unbelief for ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us out of <hi>Canaan.
<note place="margin">Heb: 3: 19:</note> They could not enter in becauſe of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</hi> No wonder that Gods promiſes, the only ſolid grounds o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> comfort in times of tryal, do not, cannot, comfort us: alas!
<note place="margin">Pſal: 27: 13:</note> they have no credit with us. We <hi>faint,</hi> becauſe we <hi>believe not.</hi> O that this ſin may be your ſin no more! <hi>Take heed, brethren, leſt there be in any of you</hi> for the future <hi>an evil heart of unbelief in departing from the living God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr: 3: 12:</note> and thereby God be provoked to depart further and further from you, until he hath left you <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally and finally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſetledneſs in Religion</hi> Hath not this been your ſin, yea,
<note place="margin">Againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetledneſs.</note> is it not ſtill your ſin? Who <hi>believes without wavering,</hi> without any fear leſt the contrary ſhould prove true? Are not you trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a <hi>Vertigo</hi> in your <hi>Heads,</hi> a <hi>giddineſs</hi> in your <hi>underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</hi> Have not ſome thought <hi>ſcepticiſme</hi> very tollerable?
<note place="margin">1 Cor: 16: 13: Col: 2: 6, 7, 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2 Theſ: 2: 2:</note> Hath not the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>ſtand faſt in the faith: Be eſtabliſhed in the faith, as you have been taught, &amp;c. Beware lest any ſpoyle you through philoſophy and vain deceit: be not ſoon ſhaken in mind?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Brinſley</hi>'s ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Vertigo: <hi>p:</hi> 9, 10, 11, &amp;c.</note> And yet have not many been for an <hi>Academical</hi> and <hi>Pyrrhonian</hi> demur and dubitation concerning Scripture Revelations? Have not more been actually <hi>carried about,</hi> as <hi>wheels,</hi> as <hi>chaff,</hi> as <hi>waves,</hi> as <hi>clouds, with every wind of doctrine?</hi> Have not you <hi>turned round,</hi> as <hi>wheels,</hi> with the <hi>times</hi> and <hi>places,</hi> where you lived? Have not you been <hi>up</hi> and <hi>down;</hi> now of <hi>this</hi> mind, then of <hi>that,</hi> embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and following thoſe opinions, and ways, which the times have ſmiled upon? Have not you been <hi>whirld about</hi> by the <hi>times,</hi> as <hi>chaff</hi> by the <hi>wind?</hi> Have not you been <hi>wavering,
<note place="margin">Jam: 1: 6.</note> as a wave of the Sea,</hi> which is never ſtanding ſtill, if there be any wind ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring? Have not ſome of you been carried quite round about the Card and Compaſs, as the <hi>Clouds</hi> of the Aire are from one quarter of the Heaven to another?
<note place="margin">Hebr: 13.9.</note> Have not you been thus <hi>carried about with divers and ſtrange Doctrines,</hi> with Doctrines <hi>differing</hi> from the truth, and <hi>ſtrange</hi> to the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament? Are not you yet uneſtabliſhed, yea, are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61858:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>not you careleſs in ſeeking after eſtabliſhment? Are not you ſtil even indifferent whether you <hi>pray</hi> to God to eſtabliſh you, as <hi>David</hi> did, yea, or no? Whether you <hi>enjoy the Sacrament</hi> of the Lords Supper (that <hi>heart-eſtabliſhing Ordinance</hi>) duly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, yea, or no? Whether you <hi>continue fellowſhip</hi> with eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Chriſtians, yea, or no? Do not you ſtill <hi>ſtagger</hi> at the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> of God, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>God will be a Sun and a Shield, and no good thing will be with-hold from them that walk uprightly:</hi> that <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon is fallen, is fallen, i. e.</hi> ſhall as certainly fall, and that utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if ſhe were ſo fallen already: that <hi>there ſhall be a reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dry bones, &amp;c</hi> Do not you ſtil <hi>diſpute</hi> the promiſes in your thoughts? Do not you ſtil doubt whether God will be as good as his word, and that becauſe of the difficultie, that lie in the way? All <hi>staggering</hi> at the promiſes of God is from <hi>unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.
<note place="margin">Rom: 4: 20: <hi>Brinſley, &amp;c. p:</hi> 98:</note> He ſtaggered not at the promiſe of God through unbelief.</hi> Is not this alſo a matter of juſt and deep Lamentation to ſee ſo many Profeſſors, ſome of which were formerly looked upon as ſober and ſtayed Chriſtians, now <hi>reeling</hi> and <hi>ſtaggering</hi> (like <hi>drunken</hi> Men) <hi>to</hi> and <hi>fro,</hi> carried <hi>this</hi> way, and <hi>that</hi> way, as the <hi>wind</hi> blows? ſhould any of you, whilſt your ſelves ſtand ſafe upon the ſhore, ſee others though <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> much more if <hi>friends, toſſed</hi> upon the <hi>waves,</hi> among <hi>rocks</hi> and <hi>quick ſands,</hi> ready to periſh every moment; might it not be preſumed, that it would affect, the flintie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart among you? and can you ſee the <hi>ſouls</hi> of your <hi>brethren</hi> and <hi>ſiſters</hi> thus <hi>toſſed</hi> to and fro without any <hi>trouble</hi> to <hi>your own</hi> ſouls? But alas! who ſtands faſt and ſafe upon the ſhoar? Are not all your hearts unſetled? And what! will yee not pity your own unſtable ſouls? Is it nothing to you, to be under <hi>Reubens</hi> reproach?
<note place="margin">Gen: 49. 4: Jam: 1: 8:</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtable as water, thou ſhalt not excel. A double minded Man is unſtable in all his ways.</hi> Are not you in danger of being utterly ruined in <hi>this hour of temptation, that is come upon all the World,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.8. <hi>Ne ſit, qui vos depraedetur. Beza in loc.</hi> mar: 3: 5:</note> to try them that dwell upon the Earth?</hi> Are not you in danger of being <hi>ſpoyled,</hi> of being <hi>made a prey?</hi> O! your unbelieving ſtaggerings grieve the heart of your Lord. The Holy Ghoſt, ſpeaking of the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> tells us, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was grieved for the hardneſs of their hearts:</hi> And ſhall they not grieve your hearts? It is a wonder that God hath ſpared you ſo long. <hi>O faithleſs and perverſe Generation! How long ſhall I be with you? How long ſhall I ſuffer you?</hi> O! <hi>ſin no more</hi> in this kind. O that <hi>henceforth yee be no more children teſſed to and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61858:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.14. <hi>Brinſley,</hi> &amp;c. 206, &amp;c. Hebr. 13.9. 1 Theſ. 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Col. 2.2.</note> by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lye in wait to deceive! O! Be not carried about with divers and ſtrange Doctrines for it is a good thing, that the heart be establiſhed with grace.</hi> Be reſtleſs, till the <hi>Word come unto you in much aſſurance:</hi> Be reſtleſs, till you have attained <hi>unto all the riches of the full aſſurance of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to the acknowledgement of the myſtery of God,</hi> &amp;c. Seek heart-eſtabliſhment from God, for yourſelves and others, as <hi>Peter</hi> doth, <hi>Now the God of all grace,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>make you perfect,
<note place="margin">1 Peter 5.10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Pſa. 51.12.</note> ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, ſtrengthen you:</hi> And <hi>David, Stabliſh me with thy free Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Neglect neither the <hi>Word,</hi> nor <hi>Sacrament,</hi> adminiſtred after the right order. O!
<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.25:</note> 
                  <hi>Forſake not the aſſembling of your ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is. Trees</hi> ſtand ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er in the <hi>Wood</hi> or <hi>Grove,</hi> where they have company, than in the <hi>Field,</hi> where they ſtand alone.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Reſting in a Dead Faith.</hi> Hath not this been your ſin?
<note place="margin">Againſt reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Dead Faith. <hi>Manton</hi> on <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.17.</note> Have not you ſatisfied your ſelves with a Faith, that is but the <hi>carkaſs</hi> of ſaving believing? The Apoſtle, in making mention of a <hi>dead faith,</hi> alludeth to a <hi>corps,</hi> or a <hi>dead plant,</hi> which have only an outward <hi>ſimilitude</hi> and <hi>likeneſs</hi> to thoſe which are <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. Saving belief is an aſſent wrought in the Soul, by the ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, and built upon a Divine Teſtimony.</hi> But is not our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, the <hi>effect</hi> of natural <hi>reaſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>White</hi>'s Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, p. 91, 92, &amp;c. 1 John 5: 1:</note> further <hi>enlightned</hi> (at moſt) by the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of the <hi>Spirit?</hi> Do not we remain <hi>unſanctified,</hi> notwithſtanding our believing? <hi>Whoſoever believes that Jeſus is the Chriſt, is born of God.</hi> Have we any further aſſurance of what we believe, than that which Reaſon ſuggeſts? Were ever the things believed, evident to any ſpiritual ſenſe within us? <hi>Faith is the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr: 11: 1:</note> Is not our belief ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only upon an <hi>humane</hi> teſtimony? <hi>We call that a Divine Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>White,</hi> &amp;c: p. 95, 96, &amp;c.</note> (ſaith <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>Western</hi> Worthies) <hi>which is given by the Spirit of God, to that Spirit which is within a regenerate perſon; For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>unto any teſtimony two things are required;</hi> Firſt, <hi>The manifeſting and preſenting that which is to be credited or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</hi> Secondly, <hi>An ability in him, to whom it is witneſſed, to underſtand it; otherwiſe the propoſing any thing by diſcourſe to a bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that wants reaſon to underſtand ſpeech, or the relating of any thing to a man, that hath reaſon, in the</hi> Greek <hi>tongue, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands no language but</hi> Engliſh, <hi>is no teſtimony, no more than it is to a deaf man, that cannot hear: Wherefore, to make a Divine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61858:11"/>teſtimony, there muſt be both Gods teſtifying unto man, and alſo a mind in him able to underſtand that Revelation.</hi> Firſt, <hi>The Spirit of God must reveal and manifeſt unto a man that Truth, that is to be believed, as the light diſcovers any viſible object:</hi> Next, <hi>There muſt be in that man, a light planted in his heart,</hi> (<hi>which the Apoſtle calls,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Jo: 5: 20:</note> An underſtanding to know him, that is true) <hi>as the light or viſnal-faculty is planted in the eye, or elſe he cannot comprehend that light, that ſhines unto him. — The evidence then, which a true believer hath of any truth of God, which he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth, is the manifesting of that truth unto the Spirit, not only by a form of words, to the natural underſtanding, but beyond that, by a kind of demonſtration unto the ſpiritual mind; as the evidence of any object to the eye, is by the ſhining of the light upon it, which makes it to appear to be ſuch as it is. This kind of teſtifying, or evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencing things,
<note place="margin">Rom: 8: 16:</note> in a ſpiritual way, the Apoſtle calls,</hi> The wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing of Gods Spirit, with our Spirit, <hi>mentioning expreſly two Spirits, whereof, if either be wanting, there can be no Divine te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony.</hi> But is not our <hi>belief grounded</hi> upon the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> upon the conſonancy of Scripture-revelations to right Reaſon? And is not the teſtimony of <hi>reaſon</hi> an <hi>humane</hi> teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? Yea, Do not we believe upon an humane teſtimony, when we believe any thing written in the Scriptures, for the <hi>teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> If that we believe the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, upon the <hi>general conſent of the Church,</hi> or <hi>upon the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and reaſonableneſs of the things therein delivered,</hi> or <hi>upon the obſervation of the truth of thoſe writings in moſt things,</hi> which all make up but an <hi>humane</hi> teſtimony? This the ſame learned and judicious Divine proves thus,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>White, &amp;c:</hi> p: 98, 99:</note> 
                  <q>The aſſent unto one thing for another, is built upon that, to which we firſt give our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: as a ſtone in a wall, though it lyes immediately upon that ſtone, that is next under it, yet it is indeed ſupported by the foundation, which bears up all the building.</q> We ſay, we do <hi>believe;</hi> but is not our Aſſent <hi>without ſutable impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon our hearts,</hi> and <hi>without a ſutable carriage in our lives?</hi> Doth the <hi>reality</hi> of Gods being believed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Liſe, <hi>on</hi> John 17: 3:</note> make us look upon our ſelves, and all things, as <hi>nothing without God,</hi> as <hi>nothing in compariſon of God;</hi> and to let the <hi>beeing</hi> and <hi>reality</hi> of our <hi>love, deſire,</hi> and <hi>endeavours,</hi> be let out upon the moſt <hi>real</hi> and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent <hi>Beeing?</hi> Doth the belief of Gods <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> contract and <hi>unite</hi> our ſtragling affections, and call them home from <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61858:11"/>Vanity? Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Immenſity</hi> and <hi>Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibility,</hi> fill our Souls with <hi>admiration?</hi> Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Eternity,</hi> draw our Souls from <hi>tranſitory</hi> to <hi>eternal</hi> things? Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Simplicity,</hi> make us in <hi>love</hi> with holy <hi>ſimplicity?</hi> Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Inviſibility,</hi> make us moſtly <hi>esteem and value things inviſible?</hi> Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Immutability,</hi> beget in us <hi>unchangeable reſolutions</hi> for God? Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Almightineſs,</hi> ſill us continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>holy fear,</hi> and promote <hi>truſting</hi> in him? Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> make us <hi>delight in the wiſdome which is from above,</hi> and to <hi>chooſe God</hi> for our <hi>Teacher</hi> and <hi>Counſellour?</hi> Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> fill our Souls with a <hi>ſuperlative love</hi> unto God, and <hi>induſtrious deſires</hi> to be <hi>conform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to his goodneſs</hi> in our meaſure? Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Holineſs,</hi> cauſe us to have moſt high and honourable <hi>eſteems</hi> of <hi>holineſs</hi> in the <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and to fall in <hi>love</hi> with it, and wholly <hi>conform</hi> our ſelves to Gods holineſs in Chriſt? Doth the belief of Gods <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> make us <hi>reſolved for duty, and an holy life,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>commands</hi> of God are <hi>ſerious,</hi> and the <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>threats</hi> true? The true and ſound aſſent to any Divine Revelation, as an holy truth, includeth a correſpondency in the believer, to the thing believed: Such an aſſent deſcends from the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> to the <hi>affections,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>converſation. True</hi> Faith, and <hi>right</hi> Obedience, cannot be ſeparated; for he that believes the truth of Gods promiſes, fill'd with ſuch things as he doth moſt want, muſt needs deſire the good contained in them; and ſeeing God hath declared the effect of his promiſes, attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able only in wayes of obedience, if he neglect that means, it is manifeſt he doth not deſire the end. Certainly, if our aſſent doth not, cannot act, no more than a dead body can riſe and walk, it is but a <hi>dead faith.</hi> The Apoſtle doth not ſay (as one well obſerves) <hi>Faith is dead without works,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Manton</hi> on Jam: 2: 20.</note> but <hi>Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works is dead.</hi> I here is a difference between theſe predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as there is between thoſe, <hi>A man without motion is dead,</hi> and <hi>a man is dead without motion. Works</hi> are not the <hi>cauſe,</hi> that <hi>give</hi> life <hi>to</hi> Faith; but yet they are the <hi>effects,</hi> that <hi>argue</hi> life <hi>in</hi> Faith. <hi>Faith</hi> is not alwayes alike <hi>lively;</hi> but yet it is alwayes <hi>living,</hi> and <hi>operation</hi> is the <hi>neceſsary effect</hi> of <hi>life.</hi> O! What cauſe have we to <hi>repent</hi> of our <hi>dead</hi> Faith? And what! Shall it alwayes remain dead? Take heed, I beſeech you, not only of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61858:12"/>ſetting no your reſt in a <hi>Knowledge,</hi> but in a <hi>Faith, falſely ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> Take heed of pleaſing your ſelves any longer with the <hi>name</hi> of Faith, and remaining deſtitute of the <hi>vertue</hi> of Faith, for the <hi>crucifying</hi> your luſts and corruptions, and <hi>conforming</hi> your <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>lives</hi> to the Commandements of God. To <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> to <hi>truth,</hi> with the <hi>neglect</hi> of <hi>goodneſs,</hi> or with <hi>lazy deſires</hi> after goodneſs, is but a <hi>vain Faith</hi> That aſſent that doth not now <hi>ſubdue ſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 23.4.</note> will not <hi>ſuppreſs fear,</hi> when you come to dye. What! will ye not yet <hi>bury your dead out of your ſight?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. III. <hi>The Miſcarriages, oppoſite to Conſenting to have God to be your God, the third Act of Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Againſt reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God.</note> 
                  <hi>REfuſing God.</hi> Beware of ſtill refuſing to have the true God to be a God <hi>unto</hi> you, and a God <hi>over</hi> you; to have him to be your <hi>Portion</hi> and <hi>Soveraign.</hi> To be <hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1, 7. Rom. 9.5.</note> implies to be <hi>enough unto all,</hi> to be an <hi>all-ſufficient</hi> and <hi>ſelf-ſufficient</hi> good: and to be <hi>over all,</hi> and <hi>above all,</hi> to be an <hi>all-commanding</hi> good.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.6.</note> To refuſe God, is to refuſe <hi>to place our happineſs in him,</hi> and <hi>to come under his government.</hi> Hath not this been your ſin? God hath offered himſelf to be your <hi>chief good,</hi> and <hi>abſolute Soveraign;</hi> but have not you refuſed ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers? Yea, do not you ſtill refuſe them? <hi>There are many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of refuſing</hi> (as one well obſerves:) Although we may be free of ſome of them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ob. Sedgwick's</hi> Fountain opened, <hi>&amp;c. chap.</hi> 6.</note> yet are not we comprized in ſome one or other of them? Are not ſome guilty of <hi>refuſing</hi> by way of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous perſecution?</hi> Are not others by way of <hi>malicious oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Are not others by way of <hi>ſcornful deriſion?</hi> Are not others by way of <hi>open</hi> (though not malicious) <hi>reſiſtance?</hi> And if we be not guilty of any of theſe refuſings, yet are not we guilty of refuſing by way of <hi>diſsent,</hi> or <hi>unperſwaſion?</hi> Are not we yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſwaded to accept of God upon his own tearms? Certainly there is no <hi>medium</hi> 'twixt <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Infidelity:</hi> 'twixt <hi>receiving</hi> of God, and <hi>refuſing</hi> of God. <hi>He that is not with me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is against me.</hi> He, that doth not <hi>accept</hi> of God, doth <hi>refuſe</hi> him. That <hi>Chapman,</hi> that will <hi>not take</hi> your Wares at your price, in ſo doing, he doth <hi>refuſe</hi> them. That <hi>Woman,</hi> that <hi>diſſents,</hi> that will <hi>not conſent,</hi> that ſuch a man ſhould be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61858:12"/>her Husband, <hi>refuſeth</hi> to marry with him. Are not you ſtill unperſwaded to have God himſelf for your <hi>Portion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 3.24. <hi>Portio cujuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> dicitur in quo felicitatem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi> Calv.</note> to place your <hi>happineſs</hi> in him, and <hi>abſolute Soveraign,</hi> to come under his <hi>government?</hi> Is not this evident in the remaining <hi>deafneſs</hi> of the <hi>ears</hi> of your Souls? Not to <hi>give ear</hi> to, or not <hi>to obey</hi> the Word of the Lord, is <hi>to reject</hi> it; and to reject the <hi>Word</hi> of God, is to reject <hi>God himſelf.
<note place="margin">Pſa. 81.11.</note> My people would not hearken to my voice, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>would none of me.</hi> Were you ever yet <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually called?</hi> Did God ever yet ſpeak in ſuch a voice, as could not but be heard, as could not be withſtood? If yet your ears are deaf unto the calls of God, if yet you are able to withſtand the voice of God, certainly you do ſtill refuſe him. Do not your <hi>hearts</hi> remain <hi>obdurate?</hi> Do the offers of God make any impreſſion on them? Is any ſavour of God to be found in them? Alas! Gods offers do not move or ſtirr them cordially to defire the enjoyment of him, and ſubjection to him. Do not our <hi>worthleſs thoughts of God</hi> ſtill continue? Do not we ſtill think, that God is not worth ſo much <hi>pains,</hi> ſo many <hi>prayers,</hi> ſo much <hi>hearing,</hi> ſo much <hi>time,</hi> ſo many <hi>ſighs</hi> and <hi>tears,</hi> &amp;c. Alas! which of us accounts <hi>Gods offers</hi> the <hi>beſt bargains? That which a man counts to be his beſt bargain,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>O. Sedg.</hi> &amp;c. p. 301, 302.</note> he will</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) (1.) <hi>Make all things to give way to that</hi> (2.) <hi>Make that to fill up his deſire.</hi> (3.) <hi>It will draw forth his choiceſt diligence and pains.</hi> (4.) <hi>He will be at ſome loſs to gain it.</hi> (5.) <hi>He is peremptory, and unmoveably earneſt for the enjoyment of it.</hi> (6.) <hi>The fruition of it preſents unto him the ſweetest joy.</hi> Do we thus account cloſing with God beſt, <hi>Beſt of all?</hi> Where then are our <hi>preſent cares</hi> to get God himſelf? Where are our <hi>ſtrong fears</hi> leſt we miſs of God? Where are our <hi>full deſires,</hi> and <hi>peremptory</hi> and <hi>ſtedfaſt reſolutions</hi> to be the <hi>Lords,</hi> as well as to have God to be <hi>ours?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will we <hi>part</hi> with for God? Whence comes in our <hi>ſweeteſt joy? To them that believe, i. e.</hi> receive Chriſt, or rather God in Chriſt, <hi>He is precious,</hi> Chriſt is precious, and God in and through Chriſt is precious. But where is the <hi>precious thought?</hi> Who are <hi>reſtleſs without God?</hi> To whom are <hi>Goods not good</hi> without God, <hi>Peace not reſt</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, <hi>Life not a beeing</hi> without God, <hi>all nothing</hi> without God? <hi>Give me children, or elſe I dye,</hi> ſaid <hi>Rachel.</hi> Doſt thou ſay, <hi>Lord, give me thy ſelf, or elſe I dye?</hi> O that this may be your ſin no more! Yet conſider, and be wiſe: O! Do not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61858:13"/>ſtill ſtand out againſt him: Though you refuſe his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> yet do not any more refuſe their <hi>Maſter:</hi> Though you like not the <hi>meſſengers,</hi> yet do not any more diſlike the <hi>offers.</hi> What ſhall I ſay, to perſwade you; or rather, whereby God himſelf may perſwade you? If you will continue ſtill reſolute, that God ſhall not be <hi>a God to,</hi> and <hi>over</hi> you: verily, God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, that you ſhall not be a <hi>people,</hi> but <hi>he will make an utter end of you:
<note place="margin">Jer. 3.1, 5. Thou haſt played the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lot with many lovers; yet return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſaith the Lord. — Will he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for ever. Acts 3.19. Hebr. 10.26.</note> yet in the midſt of judgement, he remembers</hi> ſo much <hi>mercy,</hi> as once more to offer himſelf unto you, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all your former refuſals of him; and if now you will but accept of him, all that is paſt ſhall be forgiven you, and God will receive you into his grace and favour, and never any more upbraid you with your often refuſals of him: <hi>Repent ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and be converted, that your ſins</hi> (your refuſals of God in Chriſt, of ſuch ſins the Apoſtle ſpeaks in that place) <hi>may be blotted out:</hi> But if you will not, how can you read without trembling, that Word of the Lord, <hi>If we ſin wilfully, after w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have received the knowledge of the truth, there remains no more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſins, but a certain fearful looking for of judgement, and fiery indignation,
<note place="margin">Againſt clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with God hypocritical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> which ſhall devour the Adverſaries?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Cloſing with God hypocritically.</hi> Beware leſt your willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to have God for your <hi>God,</hi> ſtill prove a conſent not ſuited to the object of Faith, in its abſolute neceſſary reſpects and nature. <q>It is eſſential to God, as the object of mans Faith, (ſaith a Worthy) to be his ſupreme Lord and Rector;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, p. 62, 63.</note> and his ultimate end, and chiefeſt good: and ſo muſt be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and willed by all, that indeed take him for their God: As alſo to be perfect in Beeing, Wiſdome, Goodneſs, and Power, and of perfect Veracity: yea, it is eſſential to the object of our Faith, as ſuch, to be conſidered compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively: As that God be taken, not only as our Good, but our chief good, to be prefer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d before every creature: that he be taken, not only as our Lord, but as Soveraign Lord, to be obeyed before all other. — Where theſe eſſentials are not in the apprehenſion of the object, there is not truly Conſent, or Faith. — Conſent hath relation to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: and if it be not the offered thing, that is conſented to, but ſomewhat elſe, under that name, then it is not indeed Conſent; for there is no Relate without its Correlate. — The Civil Law ſaith, <hi>Ignorantis non eſt conſenſus;</hi> A God that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61858:13"/>is inferiour to Creatures in R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le, or Goodneſs, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireableneſs, is not God indeed: And therefore, he that takes God in this ſenſe for his God, takes but the Name of God, an Idol of his own brain, and not God himſelf.</q> Hath not this been your ſin? Is it not ſtill your ſin? Do not you ſeem to conſent, when you do not indeed and in truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? You pretend, you are heartily willing, that God ſhould be your God, and that you do conſent to have him But?</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Are not you ſtill ignorant of the true God,
<note place="margin">Ignorantly.</note> whom you ſay you conſent to take for your God?</hi> Ignorant Profeſſours can only ſeem to be Conſenters: And are not you ſtill ignorant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours? See <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Are not you for having of God,
<note place="margin">Without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting other Gods.</note> without rejecting of other gods?</hi> Indeed, had our hearts been alwayes <hi>chaſt</hi> and <hi>faithful,</hi> we ſhould not have needed to <hi>break,</hi> we ſhould only have <hi>tyed</hi> a <hi>knot;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Teates</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Map of the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſin, and way to <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> p. 338.</note> but becauſe of our former wanton dalliance with, and engagements unto <hi>other lovers,</hi> we muſt ſolemnly renounce and diſclaim them, or God will not be ours. <hi>Hearken O Daughter, and conſider, forget alſo thine own people, and thy fathers houſe: ſo ſhall the King greatly deſire thy beauty.</hi> But, <hi>Do not you ſtill refuſe to renounce the World for your chief good?</hi> Do not you ſtill <hi>ſay</hi> in your hearts and deſires, <hi>Who will ſhew us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa: 45.10, 11, Other chief goods. Pſa. 4.6.</note> who will give us to enjoy, <hi>any good,</hi> the good of the creature, an earthly happineſs? Do not you ſtill ſay in your hearts, <hi>Take God for a portion, who will, ſo we may have our portion in this life?</hi> Was not he guilty of blaſphemy, that ſaid, He would not part with his part in <hi>Paris,</hi> for a part in <hi>Paradiſe?</hi> And are not your hearts guilty of the ſame? Do not you ſtill place your happineſs, either in <hi>riches,</hi> or <hi>honours,</hi> or <hi>pleaſures?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Haec tria pro trino numine mundus habet.</note> Do not ſome cry out, <hi>Let us enjoy our pleaſures, and we matter not God and Heaven; yea, we matter not wealth or honour?</hi> Do not others cry out, <hi>Let us get riches, and we matter not grace and glory; yea, we matter not honour or pleaſure?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pulus mihi ſibilat, &amp; mihi plaud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Do not your <hi>earneſt deſires</hi> of <hi>having, carking cares,</hi> and <hi>anxious endeavours</hi> for the <hi>procuring, inordinate delight</hi> in the <hi>enjoyment, diſtruſtful fears</hi> of <hi>loſing,</hi> and <hi>repining ſorrows</hi> for <hi>parting</hi> with, <hi>this Worlds good things,</hi> ſpeak out plainly, that you ſtill place your <hi>happineſs</hi> in the <hi>creature? Do not you ſtill refuſe to renounce all other Lords?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Other Lords.</note> Are not ſome ſtill reſolved to be ruled by the <hi>Devil,</hi> to <hi>be</hi> what he would have them be, and to <hi>do</hi> what he would have them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61858:14"/>do?
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Are none of you <hi>Children of diſobedience?</hi> The original word imports, <hi>Children unperſwadable.</hi> Are not ſome ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſwadable by any Arguments to reject Satans injections and counſels? Are not others ſtill reſolved to be ruled by the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>things</hi> of the World, the <hi>men</hi> of the World? The World ſhall <hi>cut out</hi> their <hi>work,</hi> and <hi>chooſe</hi> their <hi>Imployments,</hi> yea their very <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſet <hi>limits</hi> to it: Mens <hi>opinions, precepts, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes</hi> ſhall be their <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>ſtandard.</hi> Are not others ſtill reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be ruled by <hi>themſelves!</hi> to continue their own <hi>Lords, conſulting</hi> only <hi>with fleſh and blood,</hi> doing only what is good in their own eyes,
<note place="margin">Jer. 44.17, 18.</note> as that People, who cryed out, <hi>We will certainly do whatſoever thing goeth forth of our own mouth; for then we had plenty of viciual and were well, and ſaw no evil: but ſince we left off, we have wanted all things, and have been conſumed by the ſword.</hi> But what ſaith Chriſt?
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.24:</note> 
                  <hi>No man can ſerve two maſters; for either he will hate the one, and love the other: or elſe he will hold to the one, and deſpiſe the other: Yee cannot ſerve God and mammon.</hi> Verily, you cannot be <hi>ruled</hi> by the <hi>fleſh,</hi> or the <hi>World,</hi> or the <hi>Devil,</hi> and by God too.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Without yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſelf unto God.</note> 
                  <hi>Are not you ſtill for having God to be yours, without an hearty willingneſs to be the Lords?</hi> Verily you will finde it, that it is not enough to think or ſay, <hi>I am none of Satans,</hi> I am <hi>not for the World,</hi> I will <hi>not</hi> be for the <hi>Fleſh:</hi> thou muſt come to ſay heartily,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>I am Gods;</hi> I am, and through grace will continue Gods, and <hi>none but Gods.</hi> We muſt not only <hi>leave</hi> our <hi>former lovers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Yeare, &amp;c.</hi> p. 339.</note> but we muſt <hi>return</hi> to our <hi>firſt husband.</hi> What is this (ſaith one) but the <hi>marriage-match,</hi> and in the trueſt ſenſe, the <hi>true lovers-knot?</hi> But alas! can each of us ſay, <hi>I am thine, ſave me?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.94.</note> I am not <hi>mine own,</hi> not the <hi>Worlds,</hi> not <hi>Satans;</hi> but <hi>thine,</hi> thine <hi>really,</hi> thine <hi>totally,</hi> thine <hi>ſolely,</hi> thine <hi>everlaſtingly; ſave me.</hi> Are not you ſtill unwilling that <hi>all</hi> you <hi>are,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Roberts of the Covenant.</hi> fol. 94, 95.</note> all that you <hi>have,</hi> all that you can <hi>do,</hi> and all that you can <hi>endure,</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Lords?</hi> Are not you ſtill unwilling that your <hi>minds</hi> ſhould be his to <hi>apprehend</hi> and <hi>believe</hi> him? Your <hi>conſciences</hi> his, to <hi>accuſe,</hi> or <hi>excuſe</hi> you according to his pleaſure? your <hi>memories</hi> his to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> him? your <hi>wills</hi> his to <hi>yield</hi> and <hi>ſubmit</hi> to him? your <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> his to be <hi>employed</hi> about <hi>him</hi> and his <hi>concernments?</hi> your <hi>eyes</hi> his to <hi>behold</hi> his <hi>works?</hi> your <hi>ears</hi> his to <hi>hear</hi> his <hi>word?</hi> All your <hi>ſenſes</hi> his, to be <hi>caſements</hi> and <hi>inlets</hi> to his <hi>goodneſs?</hi> your <hi>members</hi> his to be <hi>weapons o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> righteouſneſs?</hi> your <hi>being</hi> his to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61858:14"/>be <hi>only for him?</hi> Are not you ſtill unwilling that all your <hi>credit, pleaſures, riches, time, parts, gifts, priviledges, relations; &amp;c.</hi> Should be <hi>Homagers</hi> unto God? Are not you ſtill unwilling that <hi>all you can do</hi> ſhould be either for <hi>publiſhing,</hi> and <hi>maintaining</hi> his <hi>truth,</hi> or <hi>promoting</hi> his <hi>worſhip,</hi> or <hi>protecting</hi> his <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>advancing</hi> his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or <hi>fulfilling</hi> his <hi>will?</hi> Are not you ſtill unwilling to <hi>bear Christs reproach,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13 13, 36, 37, 38</note> to undergo <hi>tryals of cruel mockings, and ſcourgings, bonds, and impriſonments;</hi> if need be <hi>to be ſtoned, ſawn aſunder, tempted, ſlain with the ſword, to wander about in ſheep skins and goat-skins, in Deſerts and in Mountains, and in Dens, and in Caves of the Earth being deaitute, afflicted, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented</hi> for his ſake? <hi>To reſiſt even unto blood, fighting againſt ſin?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr:</hi> 12: 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Is not this ſtill the language of your hearts, <hi>Let us break his bands aſunder, and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> away his cords from us?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal:</hi> 2.3.</note> Which of us doth yet <hi>yield</hi> himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>unto the Lord?</hi> The genuine conſtitution of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> phraſe is, <hi>Give yee the hand unto Jehovah.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſh</hi> on 2 Chron. 30.8. Job 11: 13: Iſa: 1: 15: 1 Chro. 29.14. Ezek: 17: 18: <hi>Prov.</hi> 22: 26:</note> Are not you ſtill unwilling to <hi>ſtretch out</hi> your <hi>hands to God,</hi> to be take your ſelves to God in prayer? Are not you ſtill unwilling to yield <hi>chediential ſubjection</hi> to Gods <hi>government,</hi> as they <hi>ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> (or gave the hand) <hi>unto Solomon the King?</hi> Are not you ſtill unwilling to enter into Covenant with God to be his (which in Scripture is called <hi>giving the hand,</hi> and <hi>ſtriking hands</hi>) according to the Directions in the late famous <hi>Vindication of Piety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Is not your willingneſs to have God forced, and not free?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reedly and not freely:</note> Properly indeed every <hi>conſent</hi> is <hi>voluntary;</hi> but yet that may be called an <hi>involuntary</hi> conſent, when the will, might it uſe its own liberty with ſafety, would not conſent, though at preſent it doth. Such a conſent doth a <hi>Marriner</hi> give to caſt his goods over-board in a Storm. God <hi>wooes</hi> and <hi>wins</hi> hearts;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Teate,</hi> &amp;c: <hi>page</hi> 337.</note> he doth not <hi>raviſh</hi> them. Indeed at firſt they are not only <hi>coy,</hi> but <hi>crooked: He comes to his own</hi> (in this ſenſe, even his <hi>own intended,</hi> and <hi>elect Lady</hi> and <hi>Spouſe) but ſhe receives him not.</hi> What gracious heart is there, but with bitterneſs remembers how often it refuſed <hi>God,</hi> before he brought it to a <hi>yea,</hi> and <hi>Amen?
<note place="margin">pſal: 110: 3:</note> God</hi> only of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing</hi> makes them <hi>willing in the day of his power.</hi> But alas! are not you ſtill forced to be willing to have him, rather then to be damned? Did you ever look after God, but in a ſtrait? Have not <hi>ſin,</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> been your only <hi>delight</hi> in <hi>good</hi> days?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ob: ſedg: &amp;c: f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nut: open: pag:</hi> 303, 304:</note> and <hi>God</hi> your <hi>deſire</hi> only in <hi>evil</hi> days? In your <hi>extremities God</hi> ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61858:15"/>go for a <hi>Number;</hi> but in your <hi>proſperity</hi> he ſhall ſtand only for a <hi>cipher.</hi> Verily <hi>involuntary</hi> conſents are <hi>falſe,</hi> are <hi>none,</hi> are indeed <hi>real refuſings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Is not your willingneſs to have God defective, and not full?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Defectively and not fully: Teate, &amp;c:</hi> page 338:</note> Right</hi> conſenting is not only a <hi>free,</hi> but a <hi>full</hi> act of the will. <hi>A divided heart</hi> never yet conſented indeed to have <hi>God</hi> for its God. Surely that Chriſt, that God in Chriſt, that will not allow <hi>one man to ſerve two maſters,</hi> will never allow <hi>one woman to have two husbands,</hi> eſpecially if himſelf muſt be one of them: But alas! though you may not place your happineſs <hi>altogether</hi> in the <hi>creature,</hi> yet are not you ſtill for placing ſome <hi>part</hi> of your happineſs in ſome <hi>created</hi> good? Though you be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together for being ruled <hi>only</hi> by <hi>Satan,</hi> or the <hi>World,</hi> or the <hi>Fleſh:</hi> yet are not you ſtill unwilling not to be ruled in the <hi>leaſt</hi> by any of thoſe Lords?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ob: Sedg: &amp;c: pag:</hi> 302, 303:</note> Are not you ſtill unwilling to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>fully</hi> the Lords? Is there not ſome <hi>one thing</hi> in your ſelves, in the World, that you ſtick <hi>for?</hi> God can prevail with you for all, but <hi>one thing,</hi> in that he muſt yield unto you. Is there not ſome <hi>one thing</hi> in God that you ſtick <hi>at?</hi> you <hi>like Gods mercy,</hi> and his <hi>love,</hi> and his <hi>graciouſneſs,</hi> and his <hi>happineſs:</hi> but is there not ſome <hi>one thing</hi> in God that you <hi>like not?</hi> Do not you <hi>miſlike</hi> either his <hi>holineſs,</hi> or his <hi>juſtice,</hi> or his <hi>anger,</hi> and <hi>wrath</hi> againſt ſin? Are you ſure that you like his <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> his <hi>Spirit,</hi> his <hi>All?</hi> Alas! in <hi>this,</hi> or in <hi>that,</hi> you cannot like him, you cannot come up to him: you are content to <hi>part</hi> with <hi>this,</hi> and to <hi>leave</hi> that; to <hi>do</hi> this, and to <hi>ſuffer</hi> that; but you cannot yield up <hi>all</hi> unto God: you will part with <hi>ſome</hi> ſins, yea with <hi>all but one:</hi> you will forſake <hi>much</hi> of the World, but not <hi>all.</hi> Is not your conſent accompanied with ſome one <hi>excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or other? you will have God, that with him you may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſuch a luſt, or ſo that with him you may have ſuch a kind of life: ſo that for him you may not hazard your name, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, or your liberty, or livelihood, or your very life. If it be thus, verily you do but pretend to conſent: your <hi>ſeeming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> is a <hi>real diſſent.</hi> This one difference between God and your ſouls, will keep the breach between you from being made up, and condemn you for Refuſers of him. No <hi>bargain,</hi> no <hi>match,</hi> can be made where there is <hi>one exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly,
<note place="margin">For the future, and not for the preſent:</note> 
                  <hi>Are not you only willing to have God for the future and not for the preſent?</hi> Do not you delay to cloſe with God, as your
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61858:15"/>chiefeſt good, and ſupreameſt Lord? Do not you pauſe on Gods offers, and put him off for the preſent? Hath not <hi>God</hi> your <hi>preſent denial,</hi> but the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> your <hi>preſent Embracements?</hi> You take the <hi>preſent time</hi> to <hi>pleaſe</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> to <hi>enjoy</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> to <hi>gratify</hi> the <hi>Devil;</hi> but you do <hi>not</hi> take the <hi>preſent time</hi> to <hi>enjoy God.</hi> O Sinner! what is it that thy Heart doth at preſent chooſe and cleave unto? Is it not ſomething <hi>ſinful,</hi> or <hi>worldly?</hi> Do not ſome of you ſee a more preſent good in your Luſts, than in God? Do not others ſee a more preſent good in the World, than in God? Are not you ſtill guilty of <hi>trifling delayes?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>O. Sedg. &amp;c.</hi> pag. 281.</note> Do not you ſay to God as <hi>Foelix</hi> to <hi>Paul, Go thy way for this time, when I have a convenient ſeaſon I will call for thee?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 24.25.</note> A <hi>conſent</hi> for the <hi>future</hi> is no other than a <hi>preſent diſſent.</hi> It is indeed a moſt contemptible refuſing of God, when we do not judge his offers even of himſelf to be our chief good, and ſupreameſt Lord, worthy of <hi>acceptation;</hi> of <hi>all</hi> acceptation, of all acceptation <hi>for the preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>Is not your willingneſs to have God temporary,
<note place="margin">Temporarily and weakly. <hi>Allens</hi> Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. <hi>pag.</hi> 276, 277.</note> and weak, and not habitual, and prevailing?</hi> It is not (ſaith one) what thou art in a fit, or in a fright, or in a ſudden paſſion, in ſickneſs, or under the apprehenſions of death, that will give thee any certain Light, by which thou maiſt judge of thy ſtate, but what thou art in the ſtanding and abiding diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and bent of thy Soul. He, that hath indeed conſented to have God for his God, abides willing, is never unwilling (when he is himſelf) to be rid of Sin, the World, and the Devil, and to place his Happineſs in the enjoyment of God, and being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his government: To be ſure, his willingneſs abides greater than his unwillingneſs. But alas! Are not you only willing to have God in Fits and Moods? Do not you remain habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually unwilling? Is not your unwillingneſs greater than your willingneſs? Right willingneſs (ſaith the ſame Author) will diſcover it ſelf to be prevailing by bringing forth both <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> &amp; <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> againſt Sin: Where a man is truly willing to be rid of Sin, he will not only be patient, and give God leave to Crucifie all his beloved Luſts, and darling Corruptions, and give the Word leave to hew and ſtrike home at the root of them, without hiding them, or warding off the blow, or wiſhing they may be ſpared to him; but ſtands ſtedfaſtly on Gods ſide, and taking part with him againſt, reſolves to uſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61858:16"/>all his means for the conquering and overcoming of them: And this reſolution will bring forth reſiſtance, a reſtraining, curbing, and withſtanding of Sin in all its Workings. But were you ever thus reſolved againſt the Fleſh, the World, and the Devil, and for God? Do you yet thus reſiſt all Temptations to the contrary?</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Renouncing God.</note> 
                  <hi>Renouncing of God.</hi> Hath not this been your Sin? Even ſince you have conſented that God ſhould be your God, have not you caſt him off? Have you not returned with the <hi>Dog</hi> to the <hi>Vomit,</hi> and with the <hi>Sow</hi> to <hi>wallow</hi> again in the <hi>Mire?</hi> Have not you <hi>returned</hi> to your <hi>Former Lovers,</hi> and to be again in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to thoſe other Lords, that have had abſolute dominion over you?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Howard</hi>'s Souls miſery and recovery, &amp;c. <hi>page</hi> 134.</note> If you have not rejected God <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> yet have not you rejected him <hi>conſequently</hi> and <hi>implicitly?</hi> Thus <hi>Saul,</hi> in ſparing <hi>Agag,</hi> and the fat Beaſts of the <hi>Amalekites</hi> againſt Gods expreſs commandment,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.23.</note> is ſaid to have <hi>Rejected Gods Word,</hi> &amp; therefore God himſelf. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt rejected the Word of the Lord he hath alſo rejected thee from being King.</hi> Have not you with deliberation, for the gaining of ſomewhat that pleaſed you, done that which is indeed caſting off of God? Which of you can ſay,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.18, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Our heart is not turned back, neither have our ſteps declined from thy way, though thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſore broken us in the place of Dragons, and covered us with the ſhadow of Death? Oh! if we have forgotten the Name of the Lord, or ſtretcht out our hands to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e God, ſhall not God ſearch out this?</hi> Have not you liſted up your <hi>heel against</hi> God, after you have liſted up your <hi>hand unto</hi> God? Hath not God threatned to <hi>renounce you,</hi> becauſe you have <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced him?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.12.</note> to <hi>deny you,</hi> becauſe you have <hi>denied him?</hi> O! be at length perſwaded to <hi>remember from whence you are fallen,
<note place="margin">Rev. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and repent,
<note place="margin">Acts 11.23.</note> and do your fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t-works;</hi> and for the future, <hi>with purpoſe of heart to cleave unto the Lord:</hi> i. e. (as one well obſerves) as you have <hi>made</hi> a good choice,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antiphar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nacum Saluber <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mum.</hi> p. 6.</note> ſo ſtill to <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ick</hi> to your choice. Never more refuſe God, as the Stomach is ſaid to refuſe ſuch meat, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe of its contrariety to its appetite, it vomits up again.</p>
               <p>Now that you may not only heartily <hi>mourn</hi> for, but carefully <hi>take heed</hi> of, even <hi>virtual,</hi> as well as <hi>formal</hi> refuſals of Gods offers of himſelf unto you to be your God, conſider ſeriouſly what <hi>provocations</hi> all kinds of refuſals of God are unto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty? Muſt it not neceſſarily <hi>incenſe</hi> him, that you ſhould (as it were) tell him you will have none of his <hi>Mercy,</hi> none of his <hi>Love,</hi> none of <hi>Himſelf;</hi> you had rather enjoy the <hi>World,</hi> yea,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61858:16"/>your <hi>luſts,</hi> which <hi>diſhonour</hi> and <hi>grieve</hi> him ſo much?
<note place="margin">Jer. 44.4, 5.</note> Hath not God ſaid, <hi>Wherefore</hi> (ſpeaking of this very ſin) <hi>my fury hath been poured forth, and kindled in the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>and in the Streets of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and they are waſted and deſolate, as at this day?</hi> Yea, may you not ſear, that God will let you <hi>fall</hi> in this <hi>hour of temptation;</hi> yea, give you up unto your own hearts luſts, to commit all manner of wickedneſs? <hi>Iſrael would have none of me: ſo I gave them up unto their own hearts luſt,
<note place="margin">Pſa 81.11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and they walked in their own counſels.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap IV. <hi>The Miſcarriages oppoſite to Truſting in God, the relying Act of Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>TEmpting of God. Tempting</hi> is the ſame with <hi>trying:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt Tempting God. <hi>Ameſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> medull.</hi> l. 1. c. 12. Mal. 3.10.</note> to tempt God, is to make tryal of ſome Divine perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>unlawfully.</hi> There is indeed a <hi>lawful</hi> making an experiment of God; <hi>Try me now in this, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> This tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or trying, is an Act of Faith, leading us to obey and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe thoſe things, which God hath commanded, with expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that fruit and bleſſing, that God hath promiſed: But there is an <hi>unlawful</hi> making experiments of God. And hath not this been, yea is not this ſtill your ſin? Is not your <hi>proving God,</hi> an evidence of your <hi>tempting God?
<note place="margin">Pſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5.9.</note> Your Fathers tempted me, and proved me.</hi> Do not you ſtill make unlawful experiments of Gods power, whether he can do ſuch and ſuch things? <hi>They tempted God in their heart — they ſaid,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 78.18, 19:</note> can God furniſh a table in the wilderneſs?</hi> Do not you ſtill circumſcribe Gods power, and ſet hounds to it at your pleaſure; ſo that if God do not this or that, which you have a mind to, he ſhall not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Omnipotent? <hi>They — tempted God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſa.</hi> 78.41.</note> and limited the Holy One of Iſrael.</hi> Do not you ſtill do ſuch and ſuch things, in the moſt ſecret manner poſſible, to try whether God ſeeth what is done in ſecret, or no? <hi>They tempted the Lord, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Exod. 17.7.</note> Is the Lord among us, or not?</hi> Do not you ſtill refuſe to make uſe of the ordinary means God hath appointed, trying whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will provide for you extraordinarily? This Chriſt calls <hi>Tempting the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 4.7.</note> Do not you ſtill murmur and repine againſt God, and his Inſtruments, trying whether he will be angry? <hi>Tempting Chriſt, and murmuring,</hi> are made <hi>Synonima's.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.9, 10.</note> If you do not ſtill tempt God <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>intentionally,</hi> yet do not you
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61858:17"/>ſtill tempt him <hi>conſequently</hi> and <hi>implicitely?</hi> Do not you ſtill do that, which of it ſelf; and in its own nature, tends to try, either Gods <hi>Power,</hi> or his <hi>Omniſcience</hi> and <hi>Omni-preſence,</hi> or his <hi>Providence,</hi> or his <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Anger,</hi> of what mettal he is made? This notion of tempting God, may be farther cleared by conſidering,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>White</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.7.</note> what it is to tempt man: <hi>To tempt man, is to deſire, and ſome way to endeavour, to incline him to break that Law, that ought to rule him:</hi> In like manner, <hi>To tempt God, is to deſire, and ſome way to endeavour, to incline him to break that Law, which he hath propoſed to himſelf to follow, in the ruling of the World.</hi> Hence ſome diſtribute temptations into two ſorts, ſome of <hi>inducement,</hi> and ſome of <hi>tryal;</hi> but the former ſort may be referr'd to the latter, becauſe the will of God is tryed in them. Thus God is tempted two wayes eſpecially, either <hi>by expecting that God ſhould do what he hath not promiſed,</hi> or <hi>by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that he ſhould not do what he hath threatned.</hi> And do not you thus ſtill tempt God? Do not you ſtill expoſe your ſelves to danger, without any urgent neceſſity, expecting protection from Heaven? Do not you ſtill do what Chriſt was tempted to by Satan? Do not you ſtill refuſe to uſe the ordinary means appointed by God for your ſafety, and yet expect that God ſhould even work miracles for your preſervation? It is true, when God takes away means of ſafety from us, then to expect ſafety immediately from Heaven, is not to tempt God, but to truſt in God; for God hath promiſed to come in at a dead lift: When God affords no means of ſafety, he will provide for our ſafety without means, if it be good for us to be ſafe. <hi>And</hi> Abraham <hi>called the name of the place,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 22.14.</note> Jehovah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ireh, <hi>as it is ſaid to this day, in the Mount of the Lord it ſhall be ſeen:</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> of which Text (ſaith one) is this,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſh</hi>'s Support for the ſinking heart, in times of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. John 4.8. Numb. 20.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Mans extremity is Gods opportunity.</hi> When Chriſt, and his company, were in the <hi>deſart,</hi> where no meat was to be had, he fed them miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly; but in the <hi>City,</hi> he ſent his Diſciples to buy meat. We may expect <hi>Water out of the Rock,</hi> where there is nothing but Rocks and Stones; but where we may hope to find Water, we muſt digg for it.
<note place="margin">2 Kings 6, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 32.</note> When <hi>Eliſha</hi> was in a little Village, not able to defend him from the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> he had <hi>chariots and horſemen of fire</hi> to defend him; but when he was in <hi>Samaria,</hi> a ſtrong walled City, though the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſent to fetch his head, he ſaid only to thoſe that were with him, <hi>Shut the door.</hi> Do not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61858:17"/>ſome ſtill expect, that God ſhould provide for their Bodies, though they neglect the means that God hath appointed for their nouriſhment, clothing, recovery from ſickneſs, <hi>&amp;c?
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.10.</note> Do not ſome look to eat, though they do not labour?</hi> But do not more expect that God ſhould provide for their Souls, though they neglect the means of grace and ſalvation? Do not you ſtill think, that your Souls ſhall do well enough, though you take no pains about them? Do not you lay all upon God, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver trouble your ſelves about them? Do not you ſtill cry out, <hi>Let us dye the death of the righteous?</hi> But are not you careleſs of living the life of the righteous? Do not you ſtill expect help from God in ſinful wayes? Do not you ſtill expect to meet with God in wayes of worſhip of your own deviſing? <hi>Now therefore, why tempt ye God,
<note place="margin">Acts 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.10</note> to put a yoak upon the neck of the Diſciples, which neither our Fathers, nor we, were able to bear?</hi> In a word, (as to this Head) Do not you ſtill do what tends to incline God to make good his <hi>promiſes,</hi> though you do not perform their conditions? Do not you alſo ſtill expect, that God ſhould not execute his <hi>threats</hi> upon you, though there be that in you, againſt which, where e're it is, the threatnings are denounced? Do not you ſtill expect to eſcape puniſhments, notwithſtanding your very ſins are threatned by God in his Word? Do not you ſtill run into temptation? And are not you careleſs to avoid occaſions of ſin, and yet remain fearleſs of falling into ſin, though God hath threatned,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 14.3, 4, 5. 1 Cor. 10.9.</note> 
                  <hi>to give up ſuch to their own hearts lusts?</hi> O that this may be your ſin no more! O! <hi>tempt not Chriſt</hi> any more, <hi>as</hi> you <hi>have tempted him.</hi> The naturalneſs of this ſin ſhould make you take heed. This is an humour, that we are all given unto by nature, to be marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous deſirous to try concluſions, that are rare and unknown; to contemn things common, and to be fond after ſtrange no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties. It was told the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> as plain as could be, that they ſhould <hi>not reſerve of the Mannah till morning;</hi> and they needed not to have reſerved it, they had freſh every day; and yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, they would needs keep it, if it were but for an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſake, <hi>to try whether it would ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ink, or no:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 16.20.</note> And though they were forbidden to gather any on the Sabbath day, and on the Eeven before had enough for two dayes, and it was told them, they ſhould find none on the Sabbath day; yet they muſt needs try. This ſin ſhould not only be the more lamented, but the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61858:18"/>more taken heed of, becauſe it is ſuch a provocation unto God. It comes from much wickedneſs. Such an one, that will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a new way to know the will of God, is not ſatisfied with Gods diſcovery of his will in his Word: yea this ſin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from pride and arrogancy, ſuch a ſoul refuſeth to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject its will to the will of God, and doth ſeek to make Gods will ſubject to its luſts. This ſin lays you open to all manner of temptations, to any wickedneſs whatſoever: neither are we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by any temptation of the Devil, unleſs we do in a ſort tempt God.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 8: 11, 12: <hi>Pſal</hi> 95.11:</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſighed for the</hi> Phariſee <hi>tempting of God,</hi> and why? Becauſe <hi>God ſware in his wrath, that their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who tempted him, ſhould not enter into his rest.</hi> It is verily height of madneſs to tempt God. To tempt God is to put God to it,
<note place="margin">1 Cor: 10: 22:</note> and <hi>do yee provoke the Lord to anger, are yee ſtronger than he?</hi> If you will needs tempt, it were beſt for you to tempt your matches. There is no dealing with Fire: it is very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to make experiments thereof: it will burn all, that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth it,
<note place="margin">Heb: 12: 29:</note> and God is Fire, yea <hi>our God is a conſuming Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Not truſting in God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in God:</note> The <hi>Hebrews</hi> expreſs this act of faith by a word, that ſignifieth to lean on, or to caſt the weight of ones body, for ſupport or ſtay. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a: 10: 20:</note> that the remnant of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and ſuch as are eſcaped of the houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſhall no more ſtay upon him, that ſmote them; but ſhall ſtay upon the Lord, the holy one of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in truth.</hi> But which of our ſouls do yet wholly rely upon God for the making good of his promiſes, either for the <hi>beſtowing,</hi> or <hi>continuing,</hi> of what is <hi>good,</hi> or for the <hi>preventing,</hi> or <hi>removing,</hi> of what is <hi>evil?</hi> Is not our <hi>not trusting</hi> in God ſtill evidenced in our <hi>ignorance</hi> of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can God be more truſted than he is known? <hi>They that know thy name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal:</hi> 9: 10:</note> and they only, <hi>will put their truſt in thee.</hi> Is it not alſo evidenced in our <hi>want of intereſt</hi> in God, by reaſon of our not <hi>aſſenting,</hi> and <hi>conſenting</hi> to him? <hi>Who is this that cometh up from the Wilderneſs,
<note place="margin">Cant: 8: 5:</note> leaning upon</hi> her <hi>beloved?</hi> who can ſuppoſe God to be thy <hi>leaning-ſtock,</hi> if he be not <hi>thy beloved?</hi> May not God ſay with a bitter ſcorn,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Teate, &amp;c: page</hi> 333, 334:</note> 
                  <hi>who art thou, that learned upon anothers beloved?</hi> How dareſt thou <hi>lay thine head in his boſome,</hi> unto whom thou never yet gaveſt <hi>the heart in thy boſome?</hi> 'Tis <hi>intereſt,</hi> and <hi>only intereſt</hi> in Chriſt, (in God in and through Chriſt) that gives a right to this <hi>act of leaning</hi> upon him. If you ſtill refuſe to enter into Covenant with God, <hi>he is ſo far from calling you to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61858:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>take hold,</hi> that <hi>he will even knock off your fingers from holding upon his Covenant,</hi> with <hi>what haſt thou to do,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.10.</note> to take my Covenant into thy mouth?</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God be thine, if thou believeſt him, and conſents to have him to be thy God, <hi>lean</hi> and welcome, and the more thou leaneſt, the dearer ſhalt thou be unto him, <hi>Chriſt loved that Diſciple beſt, that leaned upon his boſome moſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 21.20. Iſa. 49.5. Pſal. 18 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> If thou canſt ſay with Chriſt, <hi>my God</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt add, he <hi>ſhall be my strength:</hi> If thou canſt ſay with <hi>David, the Lord is my God,</hi> thou mayſt add, <hi>my ſtrength, in whom I will truſt.</hi> But if God be not <hi>thy beloved,</hi> thy <hi>leaning</hi> will be counted <hi>wantonneſs impudence,</hi> and <hi>preſumption.</hi> Is not our <hi>not truſting</hi> in God alſo evidenced in our <hi>not keeping his way,</hi> the way of his Commandments,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.3.</note> and the way of his <hi>Providence,</hi> but <hi>tempting</hi> of him? But of theſe evidences already in the former <hi>Chapters,</hi> and the <hi>firſt ſection</hi> of this. Once more, what elſe do your <hi>carking cares</hi> and carnal ſears argue, but your <hi>diſtruſts</hi> of God? Truſting in God will not indeed ſuffer you to be ſlothfully careleſs what becomes of you and yours, <hi>he that doth not</hi> endeavour by honeſt, prudent, diligent care to <hi>provide for his own is worſe than an Infidel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> But yet truſting in God would not ſuffer you to be carkingly carefull for any thing. <hi>Be careful for nothing:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> it would free you from all thoſe <hi>cares</hi> that <hi>diſtract</hi> the <hi>head,</hi> and <hi>divide</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> from other, and better things: yea it would free you from all carnal fears of evil,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ob. Sedg</hi> on Pſal. 23 3.</note> 
                  <hi>though you walk in the valley of the ſhadow of death,</hi> that is, though you meet with dangers as <hi>terrible</hi> as death, though thoſe dangers <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> you as the <hi>Mountains</hi> do the <hi>Valleys,</hi> though you be as <hi>neer to death</hi> as the <hi>ſhadow</hi> is unto the <hi>body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.7, 8.</note> though there be but <hi>a ſtep between you and death.</hi> But alas! do not your <hi>carking cares</hi> and <hi>carnal fears</hi> either <hi>divert</hi> you <hi>from</hi> duty,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as if it were <hi>a vain thing to ſerve</hi> and wait upon <hi>the Lord,</hi> or elſe <hi>diſtract</hi> you in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in reading, hearing, praying, meditating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O that this may be your ſin no more! Verily if God ſhall never be truſted in by you, you ſhall certainly, and for ought you know ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, be conſumed by him. What ſaid the <hi>Bramble</hi> when choſen King? <hi>Come, and put your trust in my ſhadow, and if not, let ſire come out of the Bramble, and devour the Cedars of Lebanon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 9.15.</note> No wonder that <hi>Fire</hi> is proceeded from God to devour the talleſt Cedars for their not truſting in him. You ſhould take the more heed of this ſin, becauſe of your proneneſs to it, and becauſe of its being the life and vigour of every ſin: all ſin is depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61858:19"/>from God; and we depart from God only, becauſe we do not truſt in him.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Creature confidence:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Againſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in any Creature.</hi> Luk 18.9. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. 52.7. Iſa. 30.12.</note> truſting in ſomewhat that is not God. Is not this ſtill your iniquity? Do not you ſtill truſt in ſomewhat, either <hi>within</hi> or <hi>without</hi> your ſelves! <hi>Do not ſome ſtill truſt in their ſins? Loe this is the Man, that made not God his truſt, but ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelf in his wickedneſs, you truſt in oppreſſion and perverſneſs, and ſtay thereon.</hi> Do not you ſtill lay as faſt hold of your ſins, as a <hi>lame</hi> Man of his <hi>Crutches?
<note place="margin">Jer. 8.5. <hi>Lye</hi> on pſal. 62.8. in <hi>M. E.</hi> at <hi>C.</hi> p. 433, 439. Prov. 3.5.</note> Do not you hold faſt deceit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to return?</hi> Do not you think that if your <hi>ſins</hi> fall, <hi>you</hi> ſhall <hi>fall?</hi> Do not you think that you cannot <hi>live,</hi> if you ſhould <hi>leave</hi> your <hi>lying, diſſembling, cheating, flattering, ſinfull compliances</hi> with ſuch, and ſuch? <hi>Do not you ſtill lean to your own underſtandings?</hi> If you do, <hi>you cannot truſt in the Lord with all your hearts: your own wiſdome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 47 10. 1 Cor. 3 19. Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> your own politick contrivances for your ſafety, <hi>will pervert you: your wiſdome</hi> will appear <hi>fooliſhneſs with God,</hi> yea <hi>emnity againſt God. Do not you ſtill truſt in your own hearts,</hi> in your own <hi>purpoſes,</hi> and <hi>reſolutions,</hi> againſt your ſins, and for God, and in your <hi>promiſes</hi> of what you will do hereafter? <hi>He that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in his own heart is a fool;
<note place="margin">prov. 18.26. Jer. 17.9.</note> but he, that walketh wiſely, ſhall be delivered.</hi> Ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>! <hi>the heart of man is deceitfull above all things. Do not you ſtill truſt in your own righteouſneſs?</hi> There is no more ſafety therein to ſecure you from the wrath of God in his Judgments in this World, than there is to ſecure you from the wrath of God in Hell.
<note place="margin">phil 3.8, 9.</note> This <hi>Paul</hi> knew, and therefore <hi>he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the loſs of all things, and ſtil counted them dung, that he might be found in Chriſt</hi> (as his only City of refuge) <hi>not having, his own righteouſneſs. Do not you stil truſt in the ſtrength, vigour, and health of your bodies?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Engl. Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi> on Iſ. 57.10.</note> May it not ſtill be laid to thy charge, that <hi>thou doſt finde the life of thy hand, i. e.</hi> Thou ſtill imagineſt, that ſo long as thou art ſo ſtrong and healthy, thou ſhalt not want ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient means to ſupport thee? <hi>Do not you ſtil truſt in your Cities, Caſtles, ſtrong holds?</hi> and yet doth not God tell you, <hi>all thy ſtrong holds ſhall be like Fig-trees,
<note place="margin">Nahum 3: 12:</note> with the firſt ripe Figs: if they be ſhaken, they ſhall fall into the mouth of the eater? Do not you ſtill truſt in your wealth?</hi> It is ſo hard to <hi>have</hi> riches, and not <hi>truſt</hi> in them, that what one Evangeliſt calls having of <hi>riches,</hi> another <hi>calls truſting in them. The rich Mans wealth is his strong City,
<note place="margin">prov: 18: 11:</note> and as an high wall in his conceit, i. e.</hi> He conceiveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as ſafe in the midſt of his wealth, as if he were in a Tower
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61858:19"/>as high as Heaven, he thinks himſelf paſt the reach of danger; but he is deceived: <hi>Riches avail not in the day of wrath.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">prov. 11: 4. Eccl 7.12. Zeph. 1.18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>im. 6.17. Col. 3.5.</note> It is true, at ſometimes and in ſome caſes money is a <hi>defence or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow;</hi> but in the day of Gods wrath, money is <hi>but a ſhadow,</hi> and <hi>no defence. Truſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> therefore any more <hi>in uncertain riches.</hi> Be not once more guilty of this kind of <hi>Idolatry. Do not ſome still tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t in their worldly greatneſs?</hi> O! <hi>woe to him,
<note place="margin">Hab. 2.9.</note> that coveteth an evil covetouſneſs to his houſe, that he may ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on high, that he may be delivered from the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of evil. Do not others still truſt in their humane Allies and Aſſiſtances?</hi> That they have ſuch Friends and Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ederate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o many ſtout and valiant Men, ready to form Armies, to ſtand by them? If the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of ſuch be your <hi>tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> the <hi>end</hi> of that truſt will be your <hi>confuſion. An H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſe is a vain thing for ſafety.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 30.2, 3. pſal 33.17. Nahum 3.13.</note> And the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uteſt Souldiers are but like <hi>an Army of Women</hi> without God. <hi>Do not others tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t in Church priviledges,</hi> crying out <hi>the Temple of the Lord, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are we?</hi> Such truſt but in <hi>lying words.</hi> No wonder that you have God for your foe,
<note place="margin">Jer. 7.4.</note> and that you are under his curſe. What ſaith the Prophet? yea what ſaith the Lord by the Prophet? <hi>Curſed be the Man, that tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eth in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> an, and maketh fleſh his Arme.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 17.5.</note> No wonder that God is writing <hi>ſentences of death</hi> upon all the means of your ſalvation: God doth ſometimes ſeverely chaſtiſe his own Children, even to prevent their <hi>trusting in themſelves.</hi> O!
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.9.</note> how carefully ſhould you take heed of this ſin, ſeeing it is ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation unto God, it being an <hi>undeifying</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and a <hi>deifying</hi> of ſome <hi>Creature:</hi> ſeeing alſo it is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that may be often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in a day, yea in an hour: and ſeeing it is a ſin that you are very proae unto? It is very much in the nature of Man fallen (as one well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſerve) to affect an <hi>abſoluteneſs</hi> and a <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reynold</hi> on Hoſ: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4: 3: <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l:</hi> 803, 804, 80<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</note> to ſeek the <hi>good</hi> he <hi>deſireth within himſelf,</hi> and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive <hi>from himſelf,</hi> the <hi>strength</hi> whereby he would <hi>repel</hi> any <hi>evil</hi> which he <hi>feareth.</hi> He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an prevailed to draw Man from God at firſt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> next unto God, every reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> unto its ſelf, we cannot conceive how it ſhould turn from God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not in the next ſtep turn unto it <hi>ſelf,</hi> and by conſeque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, whatſoever it was in a regular depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to have d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ived from God, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dien from him, it doth by an irregul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> depend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k from it ſelf. It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> natural for a ſinful Creature, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th only <hi>himſelf,</hi> and maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61858:20"/>the <hi>laſt end,</hi> to ſeek only <hi>unto himſelf,</hi> and make himſelf the <hi>firſt cauſe</hi> and <hi>mover</hi> towards that end: Yea, ſo deſperate is the averſion of ſinful man from God, that when he is convinced of his impotency, and driven off from ſelf-dependance; yet when he hath <hi>no horſes of his own</hi> to ride on, yet ſtill he will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelf unto creatures like himſelf:
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.13.</note> If Ephraim <hi>ſee his ſickneſs, and</hi> Judah <hi>his wound,</hi> Ephraim <hi>will to the</hi> Aſſyrian, <hi>and King</hi> Jareb <hi>for help.</hi> Yea, when he hath nothing in the world to turn to, but he is neceſſitated to implore help from God, he will invent wayes of his own to do it. If <hi>Horſes</hi> fail, and <hi>Aſhur</hi> fail, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to God whether he will or no, it ſhall not be to <hi>God that made him,</hi> but <hi>to a God of his own making.</hi> Once more, conſider, you never repent <hi>for</hi> or <hi>from any</hi> ſin, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you repent <hi>for</hi> and <hi>from this</hi> ſin. True Repentance and Converſion takes off the heart from all <hi>carnal Confidence;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3.</note> either in <hi>Domeſtical preparations</hi> of our own, <hi>We will not ride upon Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> or in <hi>Foreign aid</hi> from any Confederates, <hi>Aſhur ſhall not ſave us:</hi> Or in any <hi>ſuperstitious</hi> and <hi>corrupt worſhp,</hi> which ſends us to God the wrong way, <hi>We will not ſay any more to the work of our hands, ye are our gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Vain Confidence.</hi> Vain, not only in regard of the <hi>object,</hi> truſting in ſomewhat beſide God;
<note place="margin">Againſt Hyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God.</note> but vain in reſpect of its <hi>form,</hi> ſeeing, though it hath (in ſome ſenſe) God for its object, yet it wants the eſſential properties of right truſting in God: I mean,
<note place="margin">Job 8.14.</note> 
                  <hi>the truſt of the Hypocrite,</hi> which in <hi>Job</hi> is compared to <hi>the Spiders web.</hi> It's Mr. <hi>Caril</hi>'s note upon the words, <hi>That an Hypocrite hath a truſt like himſelf:</hi> He hath <hi>grace</hi> proper to his <hi>ſtate; falſe grace</hi> for his <hi>falſe heart.</hi> And hath not your truſting in God been ſuch as belongeth only to Hypocrites? Is yet your truſting in God fixed and reſolved? Is there yet any ſtrength in it? Truſt, (ſaith the ſame excellent Expoſitor) where it is true, hath a double effect, the want of which, diſcovers the falſeneſs of it in the Hypocrite: <hi>It confirms and ſtrengthens the heart againſt all oppoſition:</hi> And <hi>it encourageth the heart againſt all dangers.</hi> Doth not our truſt fail in both theſe? Are not we ſtill for going on boldly, till we meet with <hi>oppoſition,</hi> and <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> threaten us? Will our truſt, though curiouſly wrought, bear any force of battery, or ſtreſs of weather, any more than a <hi>Spiders web?</hi> Are not we ſtill guilty of not truſting in God <hi>at all times,</hi> and <hi>for all things?</hi> As <hi>true Obedience</hi> reſpects <hi>all the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61858:20"/>Commandements,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caril</hi> on Job 13.15.</note> ſo <hi>true Truſt</hi> reſpects <hi>all the Diſpenſations</hi> of God. A true believer (ſaith one) depends as much in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon God for a piece of bread, as for Heaven: He truſts God in the leaſt, as well as in the greateſt matters. But though we pretend to truſt in God for pardon and glory; yet do not we think it needleſs to truſt in him for food and rayment; either ſuppoſing that we can help our ſelves, or ſuſpecting that God will not ſtoop ſo low, as to help us? When we have a great buſineſs to ſet about, we ſtirr up our ſelves to truſt in God: and ſo we ought; but the ſpiritualneſs of truſt is ſeen, in depending on God, for managing the leaſt buſineſs, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſt duty, reſiſting the leaſt corruption, and bearing the leaſt burden. As it is the ſame <hi>love</hi> of God, that <hi>ſaveth</hi> us <hi>eternally,</hi> and <hi>preſerveth</hi> us <hi>temporally:</hi> ſo it is the ſame <hi>power</hi> of God, that doth <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſmall</hi> things for us. Can we yet truſt in God in <hi>all weathers?</hi> Some only truſt in God in <hi>fair weather,</hi> when they are <hi>full,</hi> they can truſt in God for <hi>bread;</hi> and when they are <hi>ſafe,</hi> they can truſt in God for <hi>protection:</hi> And others only truſt in him in <hi>foul weather;</hi> their truſting in God is not of <hi>choice,</hi> but <hi>forced,</hi> and <hi>of neceſſity;</hi> they never truſt in him, but when they have nothing elſe to help them. Are we yet able to ſay, <hi>Though he ſlay me, yet I will truſt in him:</hi> Or, <hi>though he make me alive, I will truſt in him?</hi> 
                  <q>It is a glorious tryal of truſt (ſaith the ſame Worthy) to ſay, Should God make me not worth a groat, yet I will truſt him; but it is a greater glory of this truſt, to ſay, Though God make me worth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, yet I will truſt in him: When we (to ſenſe) have the leaſt need of Gods help, then to truſt in him, and depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, ſhews, that we are moſt ſenſible that we need his help; for by this, we in one act, give teſtimony to the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of God, and to the emptineſs of the creature: by this we make God all, and the creature nothing at all. Faith gives a more ſpiritual diſcovery of it ſelf, when it convinceth us, that we are poor, in the midſt of our abundance, without God; than when it convinceth us, that we have abundance in God, though we are poor.</q> Verily, to truſt in God in all eſtates and turns, is proper to godlineſs. Our truſting in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſo much, doth alſo evidence, that we do but ſeem to truſt in God, and that in deed and in truth, we do not truſt in him at all: He that truſts not in God <hi>alone,</hi> doth not truſt in him
<pb facs="tcp:61858:21"/>
                  <hi>at all.</hi> Every thing we <hi>joyn</hi> with God, <hi>diſ-joyneth</hi> us from God: We can never take hold of God, unleſs we let goe our hold of other things. Which of us leans upon <hi>whole</hi> God <hi>only,</hi> and that with the <hi>whole</hi> Soul? Well, ſeeing your truſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een <hi>the truſt of the Hypocrite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 8.14. Iſa. 14.23.</note> it is no wonder that it hath been <hi>as a Spiders web:</hi> No wonder that <hi>Gods beſome</hi> of <hi>purgation</hi> to true believers, hath been his <hi>beſome</hi> of <hi>destruction</hi> unto your Truſt and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. When the houſe is ſwept, the cobwebs are ſwept aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y: No wonder that ſuch <hi>ſinners</hi> as you,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 33 14.</note> 
                  <hi>in Zion be afraid:</hi> No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>fearfulneſs ſurprizeth the Hypocrite.</hi> O! as ever you would ſtand before <hi>devouring Fire,</hi> take heed that your <hi>tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> be not <hi>as the Spiders web.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. V. <hi>The Miſcarriages oppoſite to Aſſurance the reflex Act of Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>REgardleſneſs of getting Aſſurance:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt want of Aſſurance.</note> which is called by ſome Divines, <hi>Senſus Fidei,</hi> the feeling, or perceiving of Faith: by others, <hi>Flos Fidei,</hi> the very luſtre, and eminency of Faith. When God requires all the Act, of Faith, he doth not only require, that we <hi>know</hi> him, and <hi>believe</hi> him, and <hi>conſent</hi> to have him, and <hi>relye</hi> upon him; but he requires, that we <hi>know</hi> that we do ſo. It is true, Aſſurance is not ſuch a duty, as <hi>concerns all men, at all times,</hi> and <hi>immediately;</hi> it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns only <hi>ſome,</hi> and thoſe in an <hi>order,</hi> and <hi>mediately:</hi> Though therefore it is not the ſin of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> not to know that God is their God, for that cannot be known by them; ſuch are not bound immediately to be perſwaded of an intereſt in God, unleſs we will ſay, that they are bound to be perſwaded of a lye; God being the God of Believers only; yet it is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Believers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ickman</hi>'s diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſpirits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ealing up believers. page 76, 77.</note> to let their intereſt in God to hang hovering, and in diſpute. It muſt be confeſs'd, that <hi>Gods not evidencing the direct Acts of Faith unto Believers, is not their ſin;</hi> for God may refuſe to evidence them, out of Soveraignty, or for the <hi>meer try<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> and <hi>exerciſe of grace,</hi> and nor for the Believers ſins; but yet, <hi>for a Believer to be regardleſs of getting Aſſurance, is his ſin;</hi> yea, if God refuſe, for any long time, to evidence the direct Acts of Faith, he may thank ſome ſin or other. He that bids us, <hi>Work out your ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>make your calling and election ſure,</hi> would not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61858:21"/>ſo let us be at uncertainties concerning our ſelves, did not we ſleight ſome Ordinance, or omit ſome Duty, or give way to ſome Luſt. And is not this your ſin ſtill? Do not you ſtill want that feeling or perceiving of Faith, which is not meerly hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and ſubject to falſhood and deluſions, but from Gods Spirit, perſwading the Soul, that it doth know, believe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, and cruſt in God, and therefore infallible; for the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit can no more <hi>inwardly</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſwade a ſoul of, then he can <hi>exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> bear witneſs to, any thing that is falſe? It is a good rule, laid down by a late worthy in our Iſrael,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Burges</hi>'s Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, &amp;c. <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 20, 21.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in all the Acts of Faith, whether they be direct, or reflect, the firmneſs and certainty doth more depend upon Gods ſpirit, confirming us, then upon the clearneſs of the Arguments.</hi> But which of us can ſay, that we know infallibly we are believers from Gods ſpirit perſwading us of the truth of our faith? It is true, no Man hath ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of degrees of aſſurance in an ordinary way,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>little</hi> in Morning Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe at Criple gate, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi> 12. p. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 307.</note> as that one degree more cannot be added to the former: and yet (as one well reaſoneth) there is not any repugnancy in <hi>aſſerting</hi> an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> aſſurance, and <hi>denying</hi> a <hi>perfect</hi> aſſurance; for I infallibly know that there is a God, and that this God is good and juſt, and yet I have not a perfect knowledge of a Deity, or of his goodneſ, and juſtice; for in this life we know but in part. Is not your want of aſſurance that <hi>God</hi> is your <hi>God</hi> evidenced ſtill in your <q>Not being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et above the tormenting fear of death: not yet deſpiſing the periſhing vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ities of this World: not yet ſlighting the cenſures of the ungodly:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hickman in ſupra:</hi> p. 135, to page 155.</note> remaining ſtill without an holy boldneſs in prayer: not yet taking comfort in Word and Sacraments: not yet abounding in praiſe and thanks giving: not yet kindly mourning for your ſins, nor watching againſt them: and not yet diſregarding cavils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth?</q> Is not God contending with you upon thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> account? God hath often called upon you in the Miniſtry of the Word, to give all diligence to make ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you are believers, and that God is your God upon your ſaith in him; but though <hi>God hath ſpoken in your proſperity, you have not heard:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> And is not he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing his <hi>Rod</hi> to make way for his <hi>Word</hi> to enter into your hearts? Is not he dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iving you of all your outward delights, <hi>Cauſing all your deſirable things to periſh at his rebuke,</hi> that they may not hinder you any longer from making ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, what cannot be taken away from you, that your hearts may not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61858:22"/>be taken up any longer with other enjoyments, and thereupon want either <hi>time</hi> or <hi>will</hi> to purſue <hi>the one thing neceſſary?</hi> Are not the Childs Babies taken away to make it learn its Leſſon? Hath not God made a <hi>Thorn</hi> to grow up with every <hi>Flower; the Star Wormwood</hi> to fall into every eſtate you are in, that you may yet at length ſay, it is not good to be ſo buſie to ſecure theſe <hi>bitter-ſweets,</hi> and careleſs of ſecuring an intereſt in the <hi>unmixed</hi> chief good? Is not God bringing you into life-threatning dangers, that you might not only hear with the hearing of the ear, but ſee with your eyes the neceſſity of having your inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in God cleared up unto your ſouls?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Careleſneſs of preſerving aſſurance,
<note place="margin">Againſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs to keep Aſſurance. Non minor eſt virtus, quam quaerere, pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ueri.</note> when gotten.</hi> It was your duty to be as carefull to <hi>keep,</hi> as to <hi>gain,</hi> aſſurance. When you had gained aſſurance, you ſhould have remembred that you took God to be your God, to rule you, and make you happy in the enjoyment of himſelf, not to make you rich and great in this World, and that therefore Gods people being in the hands of the <hi>Midiamites,</hi> will not evidence that the Lord is not with them,
<note place="margin">Judg. 6.13. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>bman</hi> &amp;c. p. 183. to 193. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut. 26 10, 11.</note> though <hi>Gideon</hi> ſay, <hi>If the Lord be with us, why then is all this befallen us?</hi> You ſhould have remembred that ſincere, not perfect, faith in God, intereſts ſouls in him, and that therefore frailties and infirmities do not diſſolve the union: you ſhould have been very thankfull for <hi>the firſt fruits of the Heavenly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85. 8. Eccl. 5. 4, 5, 6.</note> you ſhould have been very careful <hi>not to return unto folly:</hi> you ſhould <hi>not</hi> have <hi>deferd to pay your vows unto God:</hi> yea you ſhould have brought forth ſuch fruit after aſſurance, as you ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>did</hi> not, or <hi>could</hi> not, before aſſurance. But have not you been careleſs of diſcharging your duty herein? Have not you forgotten the termes of the Covenant you have entred into with God? Have not you been unthankful even for an Heaven upon Earth? Have not you been guilty of wilful Relapſes? Have not you refuſed or delayed to pay your vows? Have not you done as little for God, as you might have done, had the light of his countenance been never lifted up upon your ſouls? And is not God therefore angry with you? Is not he greatly diſpleaſed with you? That is his meaning, when he ſaith, <hi>he hath no pleaſure in ſuch fools.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13.12.</note> Hath not he <hi>taken away what you had?</hi> Hath not he deprived you not only of many viſible to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his preſence, but of the ſpiritual light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61858:22"/>that you may more value, and be more chary of, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, if ever you enjoy it again? And what! ſhall God loſe his end? O!
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Culverwell</hi>'s VVhite ſtone. page 152.</note> If ever God vouchſafe you any more of the <hi>hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Manna,</hi> take heed of waſting and crumbling it away: take heed of loſing <hi>the white ſtone</hi> any more: O! maintain the <hi>Oyle of gladneſs</hi> in the <hi>Cruſe:</hi> be not any more willing to part with thy <hi>ſweetneſs,</hi> thy <hi>fatneſs,</hi> and <hi>pleaſantneſs:</hi> Be never more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be <hi>left</hi> to the <hi>courteſie</hi> of a <hi>Wave:</hi> O! never more be <hi>weary</hi> of the <hi>Sun-ſhine:</hi> take heed of being once more <hi>cloyed</hi> with the <hi>cluſters</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and of <hi>nauſeating</hi> the <hi>Honey comb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Remiſneſs in recovering Aſſurance, when loſt.</hi> Hath not this been your miſcarriage?
<note place="margin">Againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſneſs in reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> and is not God therefore contending with you? Hath not God deprived you of ſealing. Ordinances; becauſe you had before driven him from his own Ordinances, and were not reſtleſs for his return? Is it not the deſign of God in taking away from you <hi>ſealing. Ordinances</hi> to make you yet ſenſible of the loſs of the <hi>ſealing-ſpirit,</hi> and that you may give him no reſt till he hath returned you both, that the <hi>Winter</hi> may be <hi>paſt,</hi> and <hi>the time of ſinging</hi> may return? Is it nothing to you to be under a ſpiritual <hi>Famine?</hi> Can you now live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>hidden Manna?</hi> Are you ſtill willing to continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a diſmal Cloud, yea to ſet in it?</p>
               <p>O that none of the three foregoing miſcarriages may be your ſins any more!</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Take heed</hi> therefore <hi>of thinking any more either that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance is not attainable at all, or that it is not tenable, when at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; or that it is not recoverable, when lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reynold</hi>'s VVorks fol. 100<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Apprehenſions of impoſſibility in either will kill all endeavours, yea deſires after it, becauſe they will kill hope. Though the will ſometimes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inordinate, may be tickled with a deſire of impoſſibilities, under an implicit condition, yet no hope, whether regular, or corrupt, can reſpect its object under that apprehenſion. It worketh two paſſions moſt repugnant to this Hatred and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair; the one being a proud oppoſition, the other a dreadfull flight from that good, in which the Mind perceiveth an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of attaining it. Treaſure up therefore the <hi>promiſes</hi> that God hath made, that Believers ſhall <hi>have, keep,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 34: 30. Hoſ. 2.19. 23.</note> recover</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance; not only that <hi>they ſhall know that God is their God,</hi> but <hi>they ſhall walk in his Light,</hi> and if at any time through their own default they loſe the Light of his countenance, that upon their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61858:23"/>Repentance <hi>he will heal their back-ſlidings, and love them freely,</hi> m ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt himſelf as graciouſly as ever. Promiſes they are of things, as <hi>future.</hi> they are undertaking of good things, which ſhall come to pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: Now every <hi>future</hi> thing is a <hi>poſſible</hi> thing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Take heed of ſlighting any more the want of Aſsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> Uncertainly, as to the truth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith, and as to intereſt in God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no light evil, it is even an inſupportable b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rden, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to thoſe that have experienced what an Heaven upon Earth there is in Aſſurance. Though one may be a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and not know that he is a Believer: and though Aſſurance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it is gained may be loſt; yet verily you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> whether your Faith in God be true, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you were Aſſured, if you can carry the want, or lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Aſſurance, as it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were no burden, and do not follow after the gaining or rec vering of Aſſurance with un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able ſighs and groa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal:</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 7: 42: 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou hid thy faith</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) and I was troubled.</hi> It wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his <hi>daily</hi> ſorrow of heart, yea it was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>death</hi> unto him. It is true, ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un into the other extream: they are too much troubled for not gaining, or loſing Aſſurance, looking on their caſe as deſperate, and themſelves as guilty of the unpardonable ſin, in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God away from them; but do you take heed of both extream, not only leſt you ſhould be troubled <hi>too much,</hi> but leſt you ſhould be troubled <hi>too little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Take heed</hi> (not only leſt your complaints, but) <hi>led your reque is for the procuring, or preſerving, or recovering of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance be heartleſs.</hi> Are you in ſears whether you be believers, whether God be your God, eſpecially in ſuch days as theſe? you ſhould be (as <hi>David</hi> was) <hi>all prayer:</hi> you ſhould even envy your ſelves the time you are forced to ſpend in eating and drinking, and ſleeping. Never expect to ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aſſurance a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt without ſuch <hi>pantings, as the chaſed Hart hath after the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooks,</hi> without earneſt entreaties, and longing, of Soul. Are you for the preſent under the light of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> countenance? De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precate hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ily an Eclipſe. Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you loſt your aſſurance? Deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e earneſtly from God new ſtamps and impreſſions: tell him, though you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt the <hi>Print, yet</hi> he hath not loſt the <hi>Seal:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 8. 77 1, 2. 88, 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> give him no reſt, till he give your ſoul' reſt. Read but the Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enned by him, when he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tion, you'l think that he <hi>breathed</hi> out his <hi>Soul</hi> with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ms.</hi> How earneſt alſo was <hi>Heman?</hi> yea Jeſus Churſt's Agony made him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61858:23"/>more to expreſs his earneſtneſs, than at other times.
<note place="margin">Luke 22: 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Being in an Agony, he prayed more earneſtly.</hi> This is one end of Gods preſent diſpenſations towards you:
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5: 15:</note> 
                  <hi>I will go</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and return to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and ſeek my face: in their afflictions they will ſeek me early: i.e.</hi> betimes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hickman,</hi> &amp;c. page 205:</note> with all ſpeed, with ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and vigour alſo, at ſuch a rate as Men are wont to do things in the morning. <hi>If your doubts do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail ſo far, as to make you leave off hearty praying, your hearty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers will prevail ſo far, as to make you leave off doubting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Take heed of contenting your ſelves</hi> (not only with heartleſs, but <hi>with fruitleſs complaints.</hi> Some (ſaith a famous Author) are of a whining temper,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Symmonds</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted Soul's caſe and cure. page 486.</note> apt to ſill the ears of all their familiars with ſad relations of their mournful caſe; but there is little elſe to be found beſides complaints: the ſoul humbleth not himſelf before God, nor contends in prayer, nor ſtriveth by the Ordinances and holy walking to finde what it always was without, or hath loſt. He compares them to the ſick man, who lyeth grieving himſelf, but no way ſeeking in earneſt to help himſelf; and to <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> crouching under his burthen. To ſpend time (ſaith another) in whining complaints,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hickman,</hi> &amp;c. page 200.</note> is more eaſie and more pleaſing to thoſe who have bruiſed themſelves; but to ſtir up ſtrength, and be doing, is more ſafe and pleaſing to God. I would not (ſo he goes on) have deſerted ſouls chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for crying out and roaring: How can they do other, <hi>whoſe wounds ſtink, and are corrupt, whoſe ſores run all the night long?</hi> But they muſt not ſpend all their time in roaring, but get the broken bones ſet, and make uſe of them; ſo ſhall they recover ſtrength and rejoyce.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Take heed of neglecting any longer any one means of Gods appointment, either for the getting, or keeping,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hickman,</hi> &amp;c. page 167. to page 173.</note> or recovering of Aſſurance.</hi> The neglect of any one (as one well obſerves) may provoke God to reject your attendances on him in the other: 'tis alſo uncertain in which God will manifeſt himſelf, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to you the truth of your Faith in him. Sometimes he doth it in <hi>prayer:</hi> ſometime in the <hi>reading</hi> or <hi>hearing of the Word of God:</hi> ſometimes in <hi>religious holy conference:</hi> ſometimes in <hi>receiving the Sacrament of the Lords Supper:</hi> ſometimes in <hi>ſinging of Pſalms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>Take heed of remaining any longer lazie and ſlothful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the uſe of the means.</hi> O!
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> yet at length <hi>give diligence to make
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61858:24"/>your calling ſure;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Culverwell</hi>'s VVhite Stone, page 150, &amp;c. 157, &amp;c.</note> i. e.</hi> your effectual calling, that your faith in God is a full anſwer thereunto. Aſſurance both <hi>requires</hi> and <hi>deſerves</hi> all diligence. Such is the <hi>darkneſs, deceitfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>inconſtancy</hi> of the <hi>heart:</hi> ſuch is the <hi>malice, policy,</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> to improve it: of ſo much <hi>conſequence</hi> is this <hi>buſineſs,</hi> and ſo <hi>dangerous</hi> is it to be <hi>deceived</hi> herein, that <hi>all</hi> diligence is <hi>little</hi> enough. So <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> alſo is this aſſurance, that no <hi>labour</hi> will be <hi>grudg'd</hi> by thoſe that do believe it.
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Antipharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> &amp;c. page 41.</p>
                     <p>See many more patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for lazineſs and to ſtir up to diligence herein in <hi>Morn. Exer.</hi> at <hi>Criple-gate.</hi> page 141.315, 316.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iiſdem alitur quibus dignitur.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> O! <hi>the rather</hi> now give all diligence to put your faith in God out of doubt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Day of great trouble is approaching, yea already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. What have you beſide, this to oppoſe to all your trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles here? When it comes to reſiſting to blood, and giving up all, can you fadge with ſuch work, while your ſpirits are dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; cloudy in this point? O my friends! Believe it, 'tis nothing but this that can make a Saint tryumph &amp; glory in abaſures &amp; tribulations. And little do you imagine how inſupportable trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are, when the ſpirit is low and dubious in point of intereſt.</p>
               <p>In particular, <hi>Take heed of being lazie, or any other ways miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying, in ſelf examination</hi> Aſſurance conſiſts in a reſſex Act, and by ſuch workings it is gotten, maintained, and recovered. The main reaſon why ſome never <hi>had</hi> Aſſurance, why others do not <hi>keep</hi> aſſurance, and why others do not <hi>recover</hi> aſſurance; is, becauſe they are not <hi>often</hi> enough, nor <hi>diligent</hi> enough in <hi>reflecting</hi> upon the <hi>deift,</hi> &amp; <hi>courſe</hi> of their <hi>hearts</hi> &amp; <hi>lives:</hi> they do not often enough rightly &amp; throughly compare themſelves with the ſure marks of true faith in God, laid down in the Word of God. Many will take ſome little pains to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inde out the marks of true faith in God, and ſome little time they will ſpend in comparing their hearts with thoſe marks, but they will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue diligent in this great duty of ſelf-examination, till the matter be brought to ſome iſſue; they will not behold their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Glaſs long enough to beget in themſelves a true no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Idea of themſelves, but go away, and preſently forget what manner of perſons they were. But let it not be ſo with you any more. Do you make it your buſineſs to go through with this work, and therefore <hi>take heed of being miſtaken as to what faith in God, and what aſſurance of faith, is.</hi> Neither make more,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hickman, &amp;c.</hi> page 120, 121, 122.</note> nor fewer eſſentials of faith in God; neither more, nor leſs, neceſſary to intereſt in God, than God hath made. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not ordinarily to have aſſurance of faith wrought, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61858:24"/>or recovered by ſome vocal, or as it were vocal, teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſpirit: or as ſoon as you be aſſured to be void of all fears, and filled with all joy in believing. <hi>Set not about this work unſeaſonably,</hi> but when you finde your hearts in the moſt ſerious and quiet frame. He that will ſee his Face in a Glaſs, muſt be fixed, and not in motion. <hi>Be ſtill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> and ſo <hi>commune with your own hearts!</hi> When you are full of dark and black tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, you are in a miſt, and not able to ſee things aright. The muddied Water is not fit to give the true ſhape of the Face. <hi>Hearken not to what carnal reaſon, and Satan ſay for, or againſt your interest in God.</hi> Before faith in God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>T. Goodwin</hi>'s child of light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> page 26.27, 28.</note> ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al reaſon and Satan uſe their utmoſt ſtrength to perſwade Souls of the goodneſs of their condition without Faith, thereby to prevent the entrance of Faith, and their ſeeking after it at all, as not needfull to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt them in God: After ſaith in God is wrought,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hickman, &amp;c.</hi> page 127, 128, 129.</note> and erected upon the ruines of all Satans ſtrong holds, and the Souls carnal reaſonings, Satan and carnal reaſon, in revenge of ſuch an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow, muſter up new Forces to perſwade the Believer by all the Objections, they can raiſe, that it doth not believe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, that its faith is not ſaving. <hi>Take heed therefore of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, and ſinful jealouſie, and prejudice upon either account, when you ſet about this work.</hi> As ſelf-love and ſelf-flattery bribreth and ſetteth carnal reaſon to plead for the intereſt of Unbelievers in God; ſo when once faith is wrought, ſinfull jealouſie doth edge and ſharpen the wit of carnal reaſon, to argue and rangle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the work of Faith; and all ſuch Objections as carnal reaſon doth finde out againſt it, are pleaſing to this corrupt principle; when you try your ſelves,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Burges</hi>'s Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: part 1 page 57, 58.</note> you will but deceive your ſelves, if you do not caſt out theſe two curſed corrupt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples out of your ſouls: if your hearts be prepoſſeſt with either, your judgments will be blinded, and become partial in paſſing ſentence upon your eſtate. <hi>Take heed of trying your ſelves by falſe marks of faith in God,</hi> of weighing with falſe weights. Hereby you may miſcarry both on the <hi>right</hi> hand, and on the <hi>left:</hi> on the <hi>right</hi> hand, if you try your ſelves by marks of perfect faith in God: on the <hi>left</hi> hand, if you try your ſelves by ſuch things as are not indeed Scripture-marks of true faith in God; for as God is the <hi>Principium eſſendi,</hi> the beginning or cauſe of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any grace; ſo Gods Word is the <hi>Principium cognoſcendi,</hi> the Principle by which we know what is true grace. I cannot
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61858:25"/>but mind you of three Rules of Direction,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ob. Sedgw.</hi> of Faith: chap. 13. ſect. 1.</note> which, a worthy now with God, hath left you in this caſe. (1) <hi>There are ſome things without which faith cannot be in the heart, and yet they do not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily and infallibly conclude that a Man hath faith.</hi> Conclude not for your ſelves by finding the <hi>antecedents</hi> of Faith. (2) <hi>There are ſome things which faith only doth produce, yet becauſe it d th not produce them always, a Man must not therefore negatively conclude from the abſence of them, the abſence of faith.</hi> (3) <hi>There are ſome things, which faith only doth produce, not as eſsential properties, but as magnificent Testimonies.</hi> Conclude not againſt your ſelves for the want of ſuch effects of faith. Be ſure that you do not any longer try your ſelves by uncertain qualifications, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not to every Believer, at all times and none but believers; but try your ſelves by ſine infallible marks by the eſſential pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties and effects of Faith in God. <hi>Set not about this work without hearty cries to God for his ſpirit to irradiate the grace you are ſearching after, and by witneſſing with your ſpirit to put you out of doubt.</hi> It is a vain thing for you to go about this work, much more to think to go through with it by any ſtrength of your own. And be ſure that you <hi>take heed of provoking God to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from you in this work.
<note place="margin">Cant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 4.4, 5, 6, 7.</note> Do not refuſe the Light of Aſſurance when offered:</hi> Hereupon Chriſt withdrew from the Spouſe; but put your ſelves in a diſpoſed an I prepared way to receive the evidencing Light of the Spirit, who will not affine you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will, or no. <hi>Do not make uſe of Signs in a prejudicial way to thoſe direct and immediate Acts of Faith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Burges,</hi> &amp;c. page 56, 57.</note> whereby you cloſe with God:</hi> While you are poring and digging into your own heart to finde faith there, forget not to exerciſe applicative Acts of Faith. When ever you would go down into your own hearts, and take a view of your own graces firſt cloſe with God himſelf in Chriſt, and afterwards begin afreſh upon the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement you have from the fight of grace within you, to act Faith upon God with a redoubled ſtrength.
<note place="margin">2 Pet: 1: 9: <hi>Mat:</hi> 25: 29:</note> 
                  <hi>He that lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe things, i. e.</hi> that doth not uſe them, ſo not to <hi>uſe</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, is not to <hi>have</hi> them, <hi>is blinde</hi> and ſoon <hi>forgetteth</hi> all the grace he hath. <hi>If God do not appear preſently do not murmur and repine againſt him.</hi> While <hi>Job</hi> thought that God wronged him, God ceaſed not to ſcare him with dreams, and terrify him with viſions; but when he juſtified God, God appeared for him. But for a more full handling of the miſcarriages about ſelf-exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61858:25"/>which you ſhould mourn for, and take heed of, I ſhall refer you to the <hi>twentieth chapter</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel-glaſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4: <hi>Reſting in an imaginary Aſſurance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary aſſurance</note> Preſumption is mainly the work of a ſtrong fancy. What the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich Believer hath by propriety and in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſame hath the preſumptuous Profeſſor in a dreaming fancy and imagination He pretends to be as knowing, as bel eving, as confident, as the true Believer; he never doubted of his Intereſt in God, none more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocond and merry then he is thereupon. Hath not this been your ſin? And is not God therefore contending with you? Becauſe we have built our houſe upon the Sands, is not God razing all our ſandy Foundations?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.8.</note> Becauſe we have been careleſs of trying our ſelves, is not <hi>God trying us as ſilver is tryed?</hi> May not we even ſay, <hi>God and upright is the Lord, that will teach ſinners his way:</hi> that by the Thunder-claps of his Righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is reſolved to awaken us out of thoſe fooliſh <hi>dreams,</hi> in which if we ſhould die, we were undone for ever? O that we may be dreamers no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger! O, take heed of preſuming once more that God is your God, either <hi>becauſe he made you:</hi> ſo he did the <hi>Devils.</hi> Gods making you, puts you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the relation of <hi>creatures</hi> unto God, and God of a <hi>Creatour</hi> unto you, but not of a <hi>chief-good</hi> and <hi>ſupream Lord.</hi> He is your Creatour,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14.</note> whether you will, or no, but ſo he is not your God. Or <hi>becauſe you proſper in every thing, and are not in trouble and, diſtreſs as other men.</hi> The more you have of <hi>a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this life,</hi> the more cauſe you have to ſear that <hi>God is not your portion. Or becauſe Chriſt hath died for you to purchaſe an intereſt in God:</hi> So he hath, if you will conſent to have him for your chief good and Sovereign Lord, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe not O! how great will your confuſion be, when your <hi>Gold</hi> ſhall be found <hi>Dreſs,</hi> your <hi>Wine</hi> to be <hi>Water,</hi> your <hi>Graces</hi> to be <hi>Corruptions;</hi> And you your ſelves appear no better then the mad <hi>Athenian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Burges</hi> Reſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi> 1. <hi>Serm.</hi> 6. <hi>Serm.</hi> 30. and 118.</note> who thought all the Ships on the Sea were his. <q>Take heed of ſuch a confidence of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in God, as hath ignorance and ſelf-love for its procreant cauſes: as is grounded on a meer natural light, or ſome falſe reaſonings: as is wrought, without any ſerious &amp; deep humiliation for being without God preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and eaſily without any oppoſition: as leaves the ſoul idle in the Work of God, without love to, and encouragement in God: as is not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with an holy fear and humility: and as is not deſtroyed by ſin, but croſſes.</q> Such a confidence is a preſumptuous confidence, and not aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Even hypocrites may have ſome experimental knowledge,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sern</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 3.</note> and yet not aſſurance of Faith: they may know that they are enlightned, and have other common gifts of the Holy-Ghoſt: that ſin is imbittered to their ſouls: that they do aſſent to ſcripture Truths: that they have ſome deſires after God and Chriſt: that they do at ſometimes and in ſome things truſt in God: and yet they want ſaving Faith, and therefore cannot know they have it. O! take heed of thieviſhly fingering the Kings Coin without a Warrant: Chriſt told the Jews, that they were <hi>of their father the Devil,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 8.54.</note> though of his Father they ſaid, <hi>he is our God:</hi> they made their boaſts and brags, that God was their God; but God and Chriſt diſowned them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. VI. <hi>The miſcarriages oppoſite to confeſſion, the external Act of Faith in God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt poſitive confeſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a call.</note>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>RAſh adventuring upon poſitive confeſſion without a Call from Heaven.</hi> Hath not this been the ſin of <hi>ſome?</hi> and have not <hi>all</hi> Profeſſors <hi>ſmarted</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:61858:26"/>for it? The Acute Author of Chriſt Confeſſed (who (as the Publiſher ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) hath cut by a thread in clearly and judiciouſly determing <hi>the preſent grand Caſes of the times</hi>) gives a three-fold Anſwer to this <hi>Queſtion, At what times are we priviledged from</hi> (and by conſequence not called unto) <hi>poſitive confeſſion of</hi> Chriſt?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſt confeſſed</hi> p. 65, 66.</note> (1) When the <hi>engagements</hi> for <hi>ſelf-ſafety</hi> are not <hi>preponderated by,</hi> or <hi>in an equal poize with,</hi> thoſe for our Saviours glory, (2.) When the <hi>intereſt</hi> both of the <hi>confeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Confeſſor</hi> will be viſibly <hi>prejudiced.</hi> (3.) When the <hi>ends</hi> of confeſſing Chriſt cannot manifeſtly be <hi>promoted</hi> by <hi>it,</hi> or <hi>attained</hi> by <hi>us;</hi> But <hi>the glory of God</hi> will be viſibly rather <hi>hindred: the Goſpel harmed:</hi> and <hi>the good of ſouls hazarded.</hi> O! ſee that for the future you do not unneceſſarily pull ſufferings upon your ſelves for your confeſſion of your Faith.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Allegs</hi> Vind. of Godl. p. 379.</note> There is (as an eminent <hi>Confeſſor</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) <hi>a ſuffering for our fault:</hi> there is <hi>a ſuffering for our Righteouſneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our fault:</hi> and there is <hi>a ſuffering for our Righteouſneſs through our fault.</hi> Run not your ſelves upon trouble when you need not, by unwary and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent managing and ordering your ſelves in the duties that confeſſion of Faith engageth you to. Be <hi>clear</hi> eſpecially in thoſe things, which may be <hi>coſtly:</hi> labour to ſee <hi>the Pillar of Fire,</hi> and the <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud</hi> going before you. Take heed of giving any juſt occaſion to others to perſecute you, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the event of ſo great a temptation is uncertain, but alſo l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt you be a cauſe that others by ſhedding your blood become greater ſinners then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they would be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npreparedneſs openly to acknowledge ſaith in God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Againſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to confeſs openly, when called thereto.</hi> 1 Pet. 3.14, 15.</note> when over he calls thereunto.</hi> What the Apoſtle ſaith concerning <hi>Hope,</hi> is true concerning <hi>Faith, Be ready alwayes to give a reaſon</hi> both of the <hi>faith</hi> that is <hi>before</hi> you, and of the <hi>faith</hi> that is <hi>within</hi> you: of the <hi>grace,</hi> as well as of the <hi>object</hi> of faith: your own acquaintance with God, believing of God, conſenting to have him for your God, and relying upon him. Though you are not bound (ſaith the <hi>grand Caſuiſt</hi>) to <hi>render</hi> an account <hi>alwayes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. C. p. 64.</note> yet you are bound <hi>alwayes</hi> to be ready; at leaſt with an <hi>habitual</hi> readineſs: though the <hi>outward action</hi> be not required at all times, yet the <hi>inward habitude</hi> is But alas <hi>I</hi> have not you been ſtrangers to an habitual inclination and diſpoſition to this duty? Have not you been without thoſe principles of <hi>ſelf-denyal</hi> and <hi>love</hi> to God, that Spirit of <hi>faith, patience,</hi> and <hi>pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that make ſouls ready for ſuch work. O that this may be your ſin no longer! Is not this one reaſon of the preſent Diſpenſations of Providence towards you, to ſtir you up by the <hi>Rod,</hi> that would not be ſtirred up by the <hi>Word</hi> to get to be <hi>ready, not only to be bound, but to die for Chriſt at Jeruſalem!</hi> The Apoſtle doth not ſay, I will be bound or I will die,
<note place="margin">Acts 21.13.</note> but <hi>I am ready is be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urd and to die.</hi> All <hi>backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> is <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ding back,</hi> when our Saviour ſaith unto us, <hi>Take up thy Groſs and follow me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Refuſing,
<note place="margin">Againſt delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing actually to confeſs, when called thereto.</note> Refuſing, or delaying, actually to make an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n acknowledgment of Faith in God, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n thereby God will be moſt magnif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d, the Goſpel beſt maintained, and the good of ſouls beſt miniſtred to.</hi> Hath not this been the ſin of ſome of you? Have not you actually <hi>declined</hi> that confeſſion, which you have been called to make? Have not you <hi>deferd</hi> your teſtimony to another time? and have not you hereby driven God away from you? ſure I am this coſt many of the Martyrs, eſpecially in the <hi>Marian</hi>-Perſecution, very dear. They did not make open acknowledgment of their Faith in God, when God called
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61858:26"/>them thereunto: and what was the Iſſue? God in reſpect of comfort left them, and they were under worſe torments, then their Perſecutors could have inflicted on them. When <hi>Jonah</hi> had a Commiſſion ſealed him to go to <hi>Nineveh</hi> with a Meſſage from God, he withdrew himſelf, and went another way; but God in the midſt of his ſecurity caſt him into the Whales belly; and when he was there, God withdrew from him, as if he meant never to own him more; inſomuch, that he ſaith, <hi>I am caſt out of thy preſence.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jona. 2.4.</note> O that herein you would <hi>ſin no more!</hi> when ever God calls you thereto, do not <hi>defer</hi> to exhibit an open <hi>oral</hi> confeſſion of your Faith in God, no,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Chriſt confeſſed, <hi>qu.</hi> 7 <hi>prop.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 69. &amp;c.</note> not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment longer, when God calls you thereto, do not <hi>defer</hi> to exhibit an open <hi>real</hi> confeſſion of your Faith in God in an <hi>active</hi> way, openly living up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Faith in God; or in a <hi>paſſive</hi> way, either by <hi>ſtaying</hi> to ſuffer, or by ſuffering in <hi>flying,</hi> as the forementioned <hi>ends</hi> will beſt be promoted. O! do not your Conſciences tell you, that if you had been more publick in your real confeſſions in an active way, you had ſuffered leſs, not only from God, but from men. Take heed of ſuffering any more upon this account.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Diſſembling in confeſſion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Againſt diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> C. G. p. 43.</note> There is a time (ſaith our <hi>Caſuiſt</hi>) for tho <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> of our confeſſion; but there is no time for <hi>ſimulation</hi> (properly ſo called) in our confeſſion. We <hi>may,</hi> yea <hi>muſt</hi> deal <hi>prudently,</hi> but not <hi>deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> Hath not this been your ſin? Hath not your <hi>converſation</hi> been <hi>in fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdom,</hi> and not in <hi>godly ſimplicity and ſincerity?</hi> Have not you at leaſt, at ſometimes gone about to caſt a <hi>vail</hi> of <hi>deceit</hi> before the <hi>eyes</hi> of men?
<note place="margin">Prov. 12.24. Iſa. 33.1.</note> No wonder that ſuch <hi>deceitful</hi> ones are <hi>under tribute:</hi> no wonder that ſuch <hi>treacherous dealings are dealt treacherouſly with.</hi> Diſſemble I beſeech you no more, either in your <hi>oral</hi> or in your <hi>real</hi> confeſſions.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Denying Faith in God.</hi> Hath not this been your ſin?
<note place="margin">Againſt denying Faith in God.</note> and hath not God therefore denyed you in <hi>this world?</hi> O! take heed of denying your Faith in God once more, leſt Jeſus Chriſt deny you in <hi>Heaven.</hi> O! Do not once more deny your Faith in God, either <hi>inwardly,</hi> or <hi>outwardly,</hi> either by <hi>word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.33.</note> or <hi>work,</hi> whether <hi>explicitly,</hi> or <hi>implicitly.</hi> Even <hi>concealed</hi> &amp; <hi>ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red</hi> (much more <hi>denyed</hi>) truths will one time or other ſet the Conſcience in a <hi>Flame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 20.9.</note> When <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>I will not make mention of him, nor ſpeak any more in his name:</hi> What followeth? <hi>Then his word was in my breſt as a burning fire,
<note place="margin">V. <hi>Caril</hi> on <hi>Job</hi> 6.10.</note> ſhut up in my bones, and I was weary with forbearing, Let him not ſpare</hi> (ſaith <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi>) <hi>for I have not concealed the words of the Holy One: q.d.</hi> If I had <hi>hid</hi> his <hi>word</hi> from <hi>men, God</hi> might juſtly <hi>hide</hi> his <hi>merci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> from <hi>me;</hi> or if I had concealed his <hi>words</hi> from <hi>others, God</hi> might now juſtly <hi>reveal</hi> his <hi>wrath</hi> againſt <hi>me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Making ſhipwrack of Faith.</hi> Hath not this alſo been your ſin?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Againſt making ſhipwrack of Faith.</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19. Rev. 2.5. Heb. 10.23. <hi>Veaning</hi> in the Farewel Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> Have not you renounced the confeſſion which you once made? And hath not God departed from you, not only for your departures from your <hi>faith</hi> in him, but for your departures from your <hi>profeſſion</hi> thereof? O! <hi>remember from whence you are fallen, and repent, and do your firſt works.</hi> What ſaith the Apoſtle? <hi>Let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our Faith without wavering,</hi> and what ever others do, <hi>let us, among</hi> whom, <hi>upon</hi> whom, <hi>in</hi> whom ſuch mighty things have been done by God, <hi>hold faſt our Faith:</hi> have we a mind to be without God again? had we rather return to be Satans, then continue to be the Lords? yea <hi>the profeſſion of our faith:</hi> faith without profeſſion, will do no more for us, then profeſſion without faith: and that <hi>without wavering:</hi> this is both a <hi>man-like</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> act.</p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
